<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Maries memoriall A sermon preached at St. Maries Spittle on Monday in Easter weeke being Aprill 1. 1616. By Daniel Price Doctor of Diuinitie, and chaplaine vnto the Kings maiestie.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113685</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10051)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1460:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Maries memoriall A sermon preached at St. Maries Spittle on Monday in Easter weeke being Aprill 1. 1616. By Daniel Price Doctor of Diuinitie, and chaplaine vnto the Kings maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Griffin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14038:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14038:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Maries memoriall.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES SPITTLE <hi>on Munday in Eaſter weeke</hi> being Aprill 1. 1616.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL PRICE Doctor <hi>in Diuinitie, and Chaplaine vnto the</hi> KINGS Maieſtie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Edward Griffin.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14038:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14038:2"/>
            <head>TO MY DEARE FATHER M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. THOMAS PRICE <hi>Preacher of Gods word</hi> in SHREWSBVRY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Loue</hi> deſcendeth, ſo duty aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth,<note place="margin">Illi debes quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abes, cui debes quod es. Amb. in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c.</note> which freeth me from all ſuſpition of <hi>flattery,</hi> in that I <hi>dedicate</hi> ſome
<hi>part</hi> of that to you, of <hi>whom</hi> I haue receiued <hi>all. Saint Auguſtine</hi> attributeth his happineſſe to the prayers of his mother
<hi>Monica,</hi> as the chiefeſt meanes vnder <hi>GOD</hi> of his conuerſion: and <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> vpon that of the Apoſtle Ep.
<hi>6.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep:</hi> 6.2.</note> Honour thy father and mother</hi> (which is the
<pb facs="tcp:14038:3"/>firſt commandement with promiſe) preferreth that
<hi>bleſsing</hi> which good <hi>Parents</hi> leaue their children by prayer before all worldly reuenues which they can bequeath them.<note place="margin">Cyr: Al. l. <hi>4.</hi> in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Parents beare the image of GOD:</hi> whom they bleſſe vpon good grounds, ſuch ſhall be bleſſed, with a long <hi>life</hi> vpon earth,<note place="margin">In co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis repoſita eſt maior com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatio cal.</note> or they ſhall haue a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in <hi>heauen.</hi> It was a <hi>bleſsing</hi> for which
<hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iaakob</hi> ſtood in <hi>competition:</hi> You haue more <hi>bleſsings</hi> then one, or one by <hi>GODS</hi> effectuall working, may worke effectually in more then <hi>one,</hi> which is the ſubiect of his
<hi>prayer,</hi> who euer reſteth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dutifull ſonne at command, DANIEL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14038:3"/>
            <head>O HOLY SPIRIT OF <hi>truth direct mee.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 26.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Whereſoeuer this Goſpell ſhall be preached in the whole world, there, ſhall alſo this, that this woman hath done, be told for a memoriall of her.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> there was a poole, which in Hebrew is called <hi>Betheſda,</hi> hauing fiue porches<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh.
5.2.</note>, many glorious things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that city of God,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 87.3.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſdas</hi> poole is not the meanſt of her monuments; <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Tertull.</note> out of the <hi>Chalde</hi> calles it
<hi>Bethſetha</hi> the houſe of ſheepe, and the text ſaith it was neere to the ſheep market: <hi>Euthymius</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Euthym.</note> 
               <hi>Beth-heſda,</hi> the houſe of mercy: and ſo <hi>Tremellius</hi> out of the Syriacke, the houſe of benig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie, giuing this reaſon of the name, becauſe the Lord did here heale all infirmities: for as Saint<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 5.3.</note>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifieth in theſe lay a great multitude of impotent folk, of blinde, lame, withered waiting for the mouing of the water: Hither came our Sauiour, <hi>Expectabant Angeli deſcenſum, &amp; ecce Ieſum noni teſtamenti angelum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beda</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Beda.</note>, they expected the <hi>Angell</hi> at a certaine time, our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14038:4"/>
               <hi>Sauiour</hi> came thither at the
<hi>ſolemne</hi> time, the time of the<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh.
5.1.</note> 
               <hi>feaſt.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Cyrth</hi> thinkes this feaſt to be <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> but<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rupertus</hi> tell vs, this feaſt was the Paſſouer, not onely becauſe by the name of <hi>the feaſt</hi> the
<hi>Paſſouer</hi> is commonly vnderſtood in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> but alſo becauſe euery <hi>yeere</hi> of his <hi>preaching</hi> heed d ſome
<hi>ſpeciall</hi> worke, againſt the time of the <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> at the <hi>Paſſouer</hi> he droue out the buyers and ſellers out of the
<hi>temple.</hi> At the <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> he fed fiue thouſand, with the fiue <hi>loaues</hi> and two <hi>fiſhes,</hi> at the <hi>Paſſouer</hi> he ſuffered, and at the<note n="l" place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm. tom.
<hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>165.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; Rup.</note>
               <hi>Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> he came to the <hi>poole</hi> of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> where the blinde, and lame, and withered, and diſeaſed lay: Bleſſed
<hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> in the <hi>Synagogue</hi> was thy <hi>ſeat,</hi> thou waſt wont to teach in the <hi>temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bir.</note> the
<hi>ſhip,</hi> the <hi>mount,</hi> the <hi>deſert,</hi> were thy places of abode, o thou <hi>faireſt</hi> of the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of men, what doſt thou in the <hi>houſes</hi> of the <hi>ſicke!</hi> in the
<hi>Hoſpitalls</hi> of the diſeaſed! O thou redeemer of mankinde <hi>thou kneweſt</hi> the whole <hi>head</hi> was <hi>ſicke,</hi> and the <hi>whole heart</hi> was <hi>heauy,</hi> therefore cameſt thou from the <hi>mountaine of ſpices</hi> to this valley of teares: All the <hi>world,</hi> was as this
<hi>poole</hi> in all parts whereof as in theſe porches, lay the
<hi>lame,</hi> and <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> our <hi>Sauiour</hi> tooke notice of the <hi>infirmities,</hi> nay <hi>tulit,</hi> nay more <hi>ſuſtulit,</hi> he tooke <hi>on him,</hi> and tooke <hi>from vs,</hi> all our
<hi>infirmities</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as<note n="m" place="margin">Damaſcen</note> 
               <hi>Damaſcen</hi> ſpeakes; he tooke on him all our <hi>miſerable,</hi> hee tooke from vs all our <hi>damnable</hi> infirmities, left <hi>no place</hi> vnlookt for to finde vs, ſought the loſt <hi>groate</hi> in the <hi>houſe,</hi> loſt <hi>ſheepe</hi> in the
<hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> loſt <hi>ſon</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> and left no place either <hi>vnſought</hi> or <hi>vnſanctified,</hi> ſanctified the <hi>houſe</hi> in his <hi>conception,</hi> the <hi>ſtable</hi> in his
<hi>incarnation,</hi> the <hi>fields</hi> by the meſſage of his
<hi>birth,</hi> the <hi>riuer</hi> by the bleſſing of his
<hi>baptiſme,</hi> the <hi>ſea-ſhore</hi> by his <hi>teaching,</hi> the
<hi>valley</hi> by his <hi>healing,</hi> the <hi>garden</hi> by his
<hi>praying,</hi> the <hi>Temple</hi> when hee was <hi>offered,</hi> and the
<hi>mount</hi> when hee <hi>ſuffered,</hi> hee hath conſecrated and hallowed <hi>hoſpitalls</hi> as holy places by <hi>Betheſdaes</hi> poole, and her <hi>porches,</hi> whether at the <hi>Paſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14038:4"/>the great feaſt hee entered and cured the man im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent for many yeeres<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 5.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed</hi> and <hi>beloued,</hi> this day is that
<hi>ſcripture</hi> fulfilled in our eares, this honourable <hi>Citie</hi> is as <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> this <hi>ſpittle</hi> as that <hi>poole,</hi> your
<hi>hoſpitalls</hi> as thoſe <hi>porches,</hi> this <hi>Eaſter</hi> as that <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> heere are the lame, blinde, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and the diſeaſed: ſhall we now pray that the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> may deſcend to moue the <hi>waters?</hi> No, the <hi>Angell</hi> hath deſcended, the bleſſed <hi>Angells</hi> of the Lord are <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> to you, that the <hi>waters</hi> are ſtird, that you haue caſt your bread vpon the waters, and the bleſſed ſpirit of God hath promiſed<note n="o" place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.1.</note> that after many daies you <hi>ſhall</hi> finde it. Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> himſelfe hath aſſured you, that when
<hi>two or three</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Math. 18.20.</note> are gathered together in his name, he will be in the midſt of them, how much more is hee now preſent, in the great congregation, hee neuer ſaw the
<hi>multitude</hi> but he had <hi>compaſſion</hi> on them, either hee
<hi>fed</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mark 6.34.</note> the multitude, or
<hi>taught</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 6.5.</note> the multitude, or<note n="ſ" place="margin">Math. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>healed</hi> the multitude, or
<hi>bleſſed</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Math. 5.3.</note> the multitude. In the fifth of <hi>Mathew,</hi> when he had <hi>healed</hi> them in the
<hi>vally,</hi> hee taught them after in the mount, and beginning to teach them hee firſt <hi>bleſſeth</hi> them, that is his firſt <hi>Sermon,</hi> wee read of,<note place="margin">Math. 4.24. Math. 5.3.</note> the firſt
<hi>word</hi> of that firſt <hi>Sermon</hi> is <hi>bleſſing,</hi> and the firſt <hi>bleſſing</hi> a <hi>bleſſing</hi> for the
<hi>poore</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Math. 5.3.</note> The cauſe of the meeting of <hi>this multitude,</hi> at this ſolemne <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> is that this honourable <hi>Citie</hi> an ancient <hi>mother in Iſraell</hi> may receiue <hi>a bleſſing</hi> for her <hi>bleſſing</hi> poured out vpon the <hi>poore: Domine ex ore infantium perfeciſti laudem,</hi> as wee may ſay with the Pſalmiſt<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note>, Lord wee haue heard and ſeene that out of the <hi>mouthes</hi> of theſe
<hi>babes</hi> and <hi>little ones</hi> thou haſt ordeined
<hi>ſtrength,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ioh 11.5.</note> and
<hi>perfitted</hi> thy <hi>praiſe,</hi> Lord wee haue <hi>heard,</hi> and
<hi>ſeene,</hi> the <hi>blinde</hi> ſee, the <hi>lame</hi> walke, the
<hi>vlcerated clenſed,</hi> the <hi>deaſe</hi> heare, and to the poore the
<hi>Goſpell</hi> is <hi>preached.</hi> O Lord holy and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend is thy name<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 111.9.</note> bleſſed be thy name for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.<note n="z" place="margin">Leuit. 21.18.</note> There was a
<hi>time</hi> that <hi>ſome</hi> ſort of people were by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14038:5"/>
               <hi>proſcription</hi> baniſhed the temple,
<hi>Cacus &amp; Claudus non intrabunt in templum,</hi> an order among the
<hi>Iewes</hi> neither the <hi>halt</hi> nor <hi>blinde</hi> muſt enter into the Temple, which Law ſeemeth <hi>ſtrange,</hi> not only ſeeing that
<hi>Caeci</hi> and <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> among the Romanes as <hi>Plutarch</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Plut. in vita Coriolam.</note> noteth were the ſurnames of chiefe families of note, but alſo becauſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> themſelues, deſcended originally from the <hi>blinde</hi> and <hi>lame,</hi> for
<hi>Iſaack</hi> the <hi>ſon</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 27.1.</note> of the <hi>father</hi> of the <hi>faith full</hi> was blinde,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 32.31.</note> and <hi>Iacob</hi> the ſonne of
<hi>Iſaack</hi> himſelfe the <hi>father</hi> o the <hi>Patriarches</hi> was lame: But this <hi>cuſtome</hi> is <hi>antiquited,</hi> and now not only, the
<hi>doore</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> is open, but the <hi>vetle</hi> of the
<hi>Temple</hi> is broken and the maſter of the fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his
<hi>ſeruants</hi> into the <hi>ſtreetes</hi> and <hi>lanes</hi> of the
<hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to bring in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beggers, and maimed, and halt, and blinde, our <hi>Churches</hi> are <hi>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> to receiue the
<hi>poore,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 14.21.</note> vnto the poore the Goſpell is <hi>preached,</hi> they are not onely cured in
<hi>Betheſdae?</hi> poole, but councelled in this place as in <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons porch,</hi> they are not onely cured in the ſoares of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dames</hi> bodie, but prepared for the companie of their brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> in
<hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome,<note n="e" place="margin">Math. 5.3.</note> and therfore I ſay with our Sauiour <hi>bleſſed</hi> be the
<hi>poore,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 41.1.</note> and with the
<hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> bleſſed be they that conſider the poore,<note n="g" place="margin">Deut. 33.1.</note> a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as ample as euer
<hi>Moſes</hi> wiſhed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>good-will</hi> and
<hi>bleſſing</hi> of him that dwelt in the <hi>Buſh,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Deut. 33.16.</note> be vpon you all, <hi>the Lord</hi> bleſſe you with the <hi>bleſſings</hi> of heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, the
<hi>bleſſings</hi> of the <hi>deepe</hi> beneath, the
<hi>bleſſings</hi> of the <hi>fields</hi> and <hi>fruites,</hi> the bleſſing of the <hi>barnes</hi> and <hi>baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,</hi> the bleſſing of <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and the bleſſings of both
<hi>teſtaments,</hi> of both <hi>lifes,</hi> of both <hi>worlds,</hi> be vpon you all from <hi>this day</hi> forth for euermore.</p>
            <p>I am not yet you ſee entred into the tent of my Text, my meditations are yet as the <hi>affring</hi> betwixt the <hi>porch</hi> and the
<hi>altar,</hi> or rather yet we bee in <hi>atrio</hi> the entrie, I muſt not go thorough the Temple, and neither muſt I ſtay at the <hi>kings pillar,</hi> nor the <hi>Prieſts altar,</hi> the holy oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14038:5"/>in this hiſtorie is neither <hi>belonging</hi> to the <hi>Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> nor <hi>Conſecration</hi> of the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> nor <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the <hi>holy place.</hi> This ſtorie tels vs of the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and his vnction was rather (ſaith <hi>Ierome) ſpiritualis</hi> then
<hi>ritualis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom. in Iſay.</note> hee was a
<hi>Prieſt</hi> neuer anointed as a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and a <hi>King</hi> neuer anointed as a <hi>King.</hi> God anointed <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth</hi> with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Peter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.38.</note> God euen thy God hath anointed thee with the oile of <hi>gladneſſe</hi> aboue thy <hi>fellowes,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Saul</hi> was anointed but with a <hi>viall</hi> of oile,<note place="margin">Pſal 45.7. 1 Sam 10.1. 1 Sam. 16.1.</note>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> with a full horne of oile, but he is anointed aboue hi
<hi>fellowes,</hi> with the oile of <hi>gladneſſe,</hi> from the crowne of his head, to the skirt of his garment.<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> Therefore ſaith <hi>Iudas,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To what purpoſe is this waſte?</hi> Anointed by the <hi>Father,</hi> anointed by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> anointed with oile of <hi>gladneſſe? Vnctio ſpiritualis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Innocentius, agit &amp; auget proculdubio quod deſignat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Im. oc. de ſacr. vncti. nu.</note> What needs this anointing, eſpecially from a woman a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>weake</hi> by herſex, <hi>wicked</hi> by her ſinne; a woman, if the <hi>moſt,</hi> and
<hi>beſt,</hi> and <hi>ancienteſt Interpreters</hi> bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<hi>ſinfull</hi> for her life, <hi>hatefull</hi> for her luſt: a
<hi>notorious</hi> enormous publike Publican, Citie ſinner. <hi>Magdalena lena, Magdalen</hi> poſſeſſed formerly with ſeuen
<hi>Deuils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 7.37.</note> ſhe of all others, ſhe to be ſo <hi>bold,</hi> to powre her oile vpon the head of her
<hi>Sauiour.</hi> Modeſt was that miſerable <hi>woman,</hi> that trembled when ſhee touched, and durſt not <hi>touch</hi> him, but the hemme of his
<hi>garment.</hi> This ſorrowfull ſolitarie ſoule in the
<hi>ſpring</hi> of her repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, waſhed his feet with her
<hi>teares,</hi> no more but his <hi>feet,</hi> ſtood behinde him,
<hi>kneeling, weeping, waſhing, wiping</hi> his feet, <hi>kiſſing</hi> his feet, <hi>anointing</hi> his feet with a box of ointment, and behold the
<hi>dew</hi> of her <hi>deuotion</hi> falleth not, the <hi>Sunne</hi> of
<hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> draweth it vp. <hi>Aarons</hi> oile was deriued from the <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>feet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 7.47.</note>
               <hi>Magdalens oile</hi> from the <hi>feet</hi> to the <hi>head: Dilexit multum,</hi> was her firſt reward, <hi>She loued much;</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> is not ruled with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14038:6"/>
               <hi>reaſon,</hi> but with <hi>loue:</hi> it neither <hi>regardeth</hi> what can bee, nor what ſhould be done, but only what it ſelfe <hi>deſireth</hi> to do. No difficultie can ſtay it, no impoſſibilitie appall it.<note place="margin">Greg. de Mar. Magd.</note>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaketh of her, <hi>Amanti ſemel aſpicere non ſufficit, vis amoris intentionem multiplicat vnctionis; Loue</hi> doubled this duties, for <hi>Loue</hi> is title iuſt enough, and armour ſtrong enough for all aſſaults, it ſelfe a reward of all <hi>labours.</hi> Affection like a fiery <hi>Cherubin</hi> flies from anointing his feet to his head. <hi>Iudas,</hi> aske no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Dilexit multum,</hi> ſhee loued much. There was no <hi>Diſciple</hi> Sathan could faſten on to betray our Sauiour but <hi>Iudas:</hi> the <hi>bagge</hi> was a <hi>curſe</hi> to
<hi>Iudas,</hi> as well as the <hi>ſoppe</hi> at the ſupper. <hi>Iudas</hi> that carried the bagge, was hee (as<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 12.4.</note>
               <hi>S. Iohn</hi> tels vs) that repined at the bountie of the loue and labour of this woman: <hi>Iudas</hi> cenſures it, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> commends it:
<hi>Iudas</hi> murmureth: Let her alone, Why trouble ye the woman, ſaith our
<hi>Sauiour:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is this waſte? ſaith <hi>Iudas.</hi> It is a good worke, ſaith our <hi>Sauiour;</hi> it might haue beene giuen to the poore ſaith <hi>Iudas:</hi> The poore yee haue alwayes, but mee yee haue not, ſaith our <hi>Sauiour.</hi> It might haue beene ſold for much, ſaith
<hi>Iudas:</hi> In that ſhe hath powred this <hi>oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> on my
<hi>body,</hi> ſhe did it for my <hi>buriall,</hi> ſaith our
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour;</hi> and addes this for a <hi>Corollarie, Whereſoeuer this Goſpell ſhall be preached through the whole world, there ſhall this that this woman hath done be told for a memoriall of her.</hi> Our <hi>Saui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur</hi> gaue many gratious <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of many in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">Iob. 1.17.</note> of <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> Behold a true
<hi>Iſraelite;</hi> of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> I haue not found ſuch faith in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> of the b <hi>Canaanite,</hi> O woman, great is thy faith; of the ſinfull woman <hi>Magdalen,</hi> Much is forgiuen her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 7.47.</note> 
               <hi>ſhee loued much:</hi> But all theſe are farre ſhort of <hi>Maries</hi> ſweet ſmelling memoriall. A time there was that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> commended<note n="d" place="margin">Luk.
10.42.</note> 
               <hi>Mary</hi> for her hearing him, aboue <hi>Martha</hi> for entertaining him, <hi>Mary</hi> hath cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the better part, which ſhall not be taken from her.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14038:6"/>
               <hi>Non opus repreh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndit, ſed munus aiſtinxit,</hi> ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. de verl is Dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i, ſer. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine:</hi> But now <hi>Mary</hi> takes vpon her <hi>Marthaes</hi> dutie, and is as much honourable in entertaining as
<hi>Martha,</hi> as ſhee was in <hi>hearing</hi> as <hi>Mary:</hi> ſhee hath choſen our <hi>Sauiours</hi> head to anoint, ſhe hath choſen the better part, which ſhall not be taken from her. <hi>For whereſoeuer this Goſpell ſhall be preached, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I finde good workes ranked into two files, the offices of
<hi>Deuotion,</hi> as <hi>Almes,</hi> and ſuch like, which be <hi>opera mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordit;</hi> and the duties of <hi>Religion,</hi> as <hi>Praiers, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſanctitie</hi> of the <hi>heart, mortifying</hi> of the
<hi>members, cleering</hi> of the <hi>conſcience</hi> from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God, <hi>furthering</hi> by all our endeuours the
<hi>glory</hi> of God; theſe be <hi>opera iuſtitiae:</hi> The former bee
<hi>manuum <hi>ſacrificia,</hi> the latter <hi>cordium ſacrificia:</hi> In the firſt the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand is only <hi>healed,</hi> but in the
<hi>ſecond</hi> the <hi>dead</hi> is raiſed: the firſt <hi>ſeedeth</hi> Chriſt in the members of his manhood, the ſecond yeeldeth Chriſt the honour of his Godhead: the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſecond
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: the <hi>firſt</hi> is the waſhing of Chriſts feet, the latter the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing of his head: <hi>Magdalen</hi> a ſinner may annoint his feet, but <hi>Mary</hi> a <hi>Conuert</hi> only may <hi>anoint</hi> his head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The firſt is as the <hi>Widowes mite,</hi> a <hi>good worke,</hi> and not <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded;</hi> but the ſecond is <hi>Salomons</hi> offering, honoured and proclaimed: the firſt as <hi>the dawning</hi> of the day, the ſecond as the <hi>ſnining</hi> of the Sunne. Both theſe haue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly appeared in this your Citie, and the former the
<hi>anointing</hi> of Chriſts feet, the <hi>feeding,</hi> cloathing, healing of his <hi>hungrie,</hi> naked, ſicke and weake <hi>ſeruants,</hi> hath beene often <hi>vrged</hi> in this place; and well it is, that ſo it is: for farre be it but wee anoint <hi>Chriſts feet,</hi> ſeeing he waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his
<hi>ſeruants</hi> feet<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 13.5.</note>: farre be it but <hi>Almes</hi> ſhould euer haue their honour. <hi>Paul</hi> was
<hi>Collector</hi> for the poore<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.1.</note>, and our <hi>Sauiour</hi> was <hi>Ouer-ſeer</hi> for the poore<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 21.4.</note>: <hi>Almes</hi> are the <hi>fruit</hi> of the Saints<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 15.28.</note>, and an odour of a ſweet ſmell, a ſacrifice acceptable, well pleaſing vnto God<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 4.10.</note>:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14038:7"/>Theſe ought you to <hi>haue done,</hi> and not to leaue the other <hi>vndone;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 23.23.</note> for as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith to vs, not my feet only,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh 13.9.</hi> Chryſoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Auguſtin. Ambr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. Orige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Chriſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but my head: for as the ſtarre of my <hi>Interpreters</hi> leadeth mee, though by diuers
<hi>lines,</hi> yet in all of them there is but one and the ſame
<hi>light,</hi> the <hi>anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Chriſts head</hi> is <hi>veneranda meditatio diuinitatis, &amp; deuota contemplatio paſſionis &amp; reſurrectionis,</hi> a reuerend awfull meditation of Chriſt his diuinitie, and a deuout contemplation of Chriſt his <hi>bleſſed,</hi> yet
<hi>bloudie Paſſion,</hi> and of his <hi>great</hi> and <hi>glorious Reſurrection. Aarons</hi> head was anointed with bloud and oile<note n="f" place="margin">Leuit. 8.30.</note>; wee muſt anoint our <hi>Sauiours head</hi> with our <hi>oile,</hi> ſeeing he hath anointed <hi>our heads</hi> with his
<hi>bloud,</hi> for the bleſſing of his bloud is vpon vs and vpon our ſeed for euer. It is Chriſts <hi>ſpeech</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Canticles, Dul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iora vnguenta quàm aromata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 4.10.</note> Thy ointments are <hi>ſweeter</hi> then thy ſpices. Of all the <hi>ointments</hi> in the whole <hi>Booke of God,</hi> none ſo ſweet as this: The holy ointment appointed by <hi>God,</hi> continued but till the <hi>Captiuitie;</hi> then the <hi>holy fire</hi> went out, the <hi>holy Arke</hi> was ſpoiled, and the <hi>holy oile</hi> ſpilt.
<hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil tam diffuſivum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Beru.</note> 
                  <hi>ac oleum,</hi> nothing of ſo ſpreading a diffuſiue nature as <hi>oile,</hi> no oile euer ſo <hi>diffuſiue,</hi> as this. <hi>Aarons</hi> ointment was
<hi>odoriferous</hi> and <hi>diffiſiue,</hi> but from the <hi>head</hi> to the <hi>beard,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>body,</hi> as it was vſed, ſo it waſted. <hi>Elias</hi> oile <hi>diffuſiue</hi> and <hi>miraculous</hi> was
<hi>ſpent</hi> and <hi>waſted</hi> not, ſpread ouer all the
<hi>houſe,</hi> for the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a <hi>Prophet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Kings 17.15.</note> a <hi>Widow,</hi> a <hi>childe,</hi> a whole
<hi>familie,</hi> a whole <hi>yeere,</hi> ſo long <hi>continued,</hi> but then <hi>confined. Eliſhaes</hi> oile was diffuſiue and <hi>pretious,</hi> and the more powred out, the more <hi>increaſed:</hi> it filled all the
<hi>widowes</hi> veſſels, all her <hi>neighbours</hi> veſſels, filled all the <hi>veſſels</hi> ſhee could borrow, and paid all the
<hi>debt</hi> that her <hi>husband had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed;</hi> but when it had ſupplied <hi>the widowes want,</hi> the <hi>fountaine failed.</hi> But neither <hi>Aarons</hi> holy veſſell of oile, nor <hi>Samuels</hi> viall, nor <hi>Dauids</hi> horne, nor the widow of <hi>Zareptas</hi> cruiſe, nor the Prophets <hi>Widowes Pot</hi> of oile,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14038:7"/>nor the <hi>Alablaſter</hi> box of the ſinfull womans <hi>ointment,</hi> ſo <hi>pretious,</hi> ſo
<hi>permanent,</hi> ſo <hi>odoriferous</hi> as this <hi>Saints oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which as the <hi>Orient Sun</hi> is euer in the <hi>full. S. Iohn</hi> tels vs,<note place="margin">Iohn 12.5.</note> that the houſe</hi> was filled with the odour of the <hi>oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> but our <hi>Sauiour</hi> tels vs, the whole world ſhall bee filled with the <hi>odour</hi> hereof, for
<hi>whereſoeuer this Goſpell is preached through the whole world, &amp;c.</hi> It is <hi>ſweet</hi> in all <hi>noſtrils,</hi> not in
<hi>Bethany</hi> only, or <hi>Galilie,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer;</hi> nor as a <hi>Storie,</hi> or <hi>Parable,</hi> but
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell;</hi> nor as a <hi>Rubricke</hi> or
<hi>title</hi> of a <hi>Goſpell,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a
<hi>Goſpell</hi> of it ſelfe, this <hi>Goſpell;</hi> nor a
<hi>Goſpell</hi> as the <hi>talent</hi> hid in the <hi>banke,</hi> or the
<hi>candle</hi> vnder the <hi>buſhell,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a preached <hi>Gospell;</hi> nor a <hi>Goſpell</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched only in
<hi>Canaan,</hi> or on the other ſide <hi>Iordan,</hi> but
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, throughout the whole <hi>world;</hi> nor ſo
<hi>preached,</hi> as that the <hi>Act</hi> ſhall bee <hi>remembred,</hi> and the <hi>Author</hi> neglected, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this that this
<hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> hath done; nor ſo <hi>preached,</hi> as that the
<hi>memory</hi> of this that ſhe hath done <hi>ſhould euer be forgotten;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhall bee told for a <hi>memoriall</hi> of her. This were <hi>enough.</hi> The <hi>oile</hi> was <hi>pretious,</hi> but the box of <hi>ointment</hi> could not be ſo <hi>pretious</hi> as now it is
<hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous;</hi> a ſtranger increaſe then the growth of a <hi>graine</hi> of muſtard ſeed, that is leaſt of all <hi>ſeeds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 13.32.</note> yet greateſt of all <hi>herbes:</hi> but this <hi>miraculous ointment</hi> farre beyond that, it ſhall ſpread ſo
<hi>farre</hi> as the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhall bee <hi>preached,</hi> through the <hi>world,</hi> and ſhall be preached as long as the <hi>world</hi> ſhall be continued. <hi>Ecce Prophetiam &amp; Prophetam, Euangeliſtam &amp; Euangelium;</hi> it is a <hi>Prophecie</hi> and a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,</hi> ſpoken by a <hi>Prophet</hi> and an <hi>Euangeliſt.</hi> All the <hi>Prophets</hi> prophecied of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and behold <hi>Chriſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecieth of
<hi>Mary:</hi> All the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> wrote the <hi>Gospell</hi> of
<hi>Chriſt, Chriſt preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> and <hi>prophecieth,</hi> and
<hi>proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi> thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Mary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and ſealeth his <hi>prophecie</hi> and <hi>preaching</hi> with an oath,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Verily I ſay to you, Whereſoeuer, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14038:8"/>
            <p>She brought a box of <hi>Alablaſter,</hi> her box not
<hi>emptie,</hi> not <hi>muſtie.</hi> Boxes of <hi>Alablaſter</hi> may be like the <hi>Phariſies Sepulchers,</hi> carrying <hi>faire titles</hi> without, corrupt <hi>carcaſes</hi> within. The box might be
<hi>pretious,</hi> the ointment <hi>poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous:</hi> but as her <hi>box</hi> was no <hi>ſtained Alablaſter,</hi> for the box was <hi>pure;</hi> ſo the ointment <hi>pretious:</hi> As the oile was enough in that <hi>little box</hi> to anoint her Sauiours <hi>head</hi> and <hi>body;</hi> ſo the
<hi>Alablaſter</hi> was enough to build a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument for her <hi>body</hi> and
<hi>memory. Babylon</hi> thought to be famous for a Tower, the
<hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubenites</hi> for their monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment built an <hi>Altar, Abſalon</hi> for his memoriall ſet vp a <hi>Pillar, Hercules</hi> vpon two
<hi>Promontories</hi> erected for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall remembrance two
<hi>Pillars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Machh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.27</note> 
               <hi>Simon Macchabeus</hi> ſet vp ſeuen pillars for a <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of the
<hi>Macchabees, Artemiſia</hi> for her husband made a <hi>Royall Tombe,</hi> one of the wonders of the world, with 36. pillars. But all, all the
<hi>Statues, Tombes,</hi> and <hi>Obelisks,</hi> and <hi>Piles,</hi> and
<hi>Pillars,</hi> and <hi>Piramides,</hi> and <hi>Ornaments,</hi> and
<hi>Monuments,</hi> in the whole world, are nothing to <hi>Maries memoriall,</hi> built out of this ſmall <hi>box of Alablaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haue yet but ſhewed you the <hi>box,</hi> at moſt but
<hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it:</hi> now as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.3:</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of the ſauour of the good ointment, her ointment muſt be powred out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this box of <hi>ointment</hi> there is the <hi>Prophecie</hi> of a <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell:</hi> The whole Bible is but <hi>Prophecie</hi> and
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> they be both in this <hi>box.</hi> Beautifull is the
<hi>box, odoriferous</hi> is this of all other <hi>ointments:</hi> Sacred is the <hi>Prophecie,</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is this of all <hi>Goſpels:</hi> neuer any prophecie ſo <hi>inlayed</hi> or invellopd with a <hi>Goſpell,</hi> euery word the <hi>Gospell,</hi> euery word the <hi>Prophecie:</hi> in which
<hi>Prophecie,</hi> or <hi>Goſpell,</hi> or <hi>Prophecie</hi> of the
<hi>Gospell,</hi> obſerue two generall parts, The two great lights of heauen, the <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone,</hi> for as God giueth light to the
<hi>Sunne,</hi> and the <hi>Sunne</hi> to the <hi>Moone,</hi> ſo Chriſt giueth light to this <hi>Goſpel,</hi> &amp; this <hi>Goſpel</hi> life to
<hi>Maries</hi> memoriall. 1. The <hi>Promulgation</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, This Goſpell ſhall be preached, &amp;c.</hi> 2. The <hi>Proclamation</hi> of <hi>Maries</hi> memoriall, <hi>Mention ſhall be made of this, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14038:8"/>
            <p>In the firſt <hi>generall part,</hi> obſerue firſt the
<hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> not a <hi>Storie,</hi> or
<hi>Parable,</hi> but a <hi>Goſpell, Euangelium Regni</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 4.23.</note>, <hi>Euangelium Dei</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1.1.</note>, <hi>Euangelium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſts</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 1.5.</note>, <hi>Euangelium ſalutis</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 1.13.18.</note>, <hi>Euangelium mortis &amp; reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis Chriſts,</hi> as my Interpreters tell mee, the Goſpell of the <hi>paſſion</hi> and <hi>reſurrection</hi> of our Lord and Sauiour.
2. The <hi>publiſhing</hi> of this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the Goſpell ſhall bee <hi>preached,</hi> not <hi>written</hi> only, and laid vp, as the
<hi>Tables</hi> in the <hi>Arke;</hi> not read and repeated only, as
<hi>Moyſes Law</hi> in the <hi>Synagogue;</hi> not endorſed on the doores, as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies</hi> were on the Temple; not <hi>inſcribed</hi> or
<hi>embrodered</hi> on the <hi>Philacteries,</hi> as the <hi>Phariſies</hi> did the <hi>Decalogue;</hi> not tied vp in the <hi>napkin</hi> of
<hi>ſilence,</hi> or <hi>buried</hi> in the <hi>banke</hi> of
<hi>negligence,</hi> but proclaimed and <hi>preached;</hi> This Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſhall be preached. 3. The <hi>extent</hi> of this <hi>preaching,</hi> This Goſpell ſhall be <hi>preached</hi> in the whole <hi>world,</hi> not in ſome <hi>Cantons</hi> or <hi>Corners</hi> of the <hi>world;</hi> not on the
<hi>Mount</hi> only, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> gaue his <hi>Law;</hi> not in the
<hi>valley</hi> only, as <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> gaue his <hi>thankes;</hi> or in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> gaue his
<hi>warning;</hi> but in the whole <hi>world,</hi> from one <hi>Sea</hi> vnto
<hi>another,</hi> from the <hi>Riuer</hi> vnto the <hi>worlds end:</hi> This Goſpell is gone throughout <hi>all the earth,</hi> and <hi>this ſound vnto the end of the world.</hi> This Goſpell ſhall be <hi>preached</hi> in the whole world.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond <hi>generall part</hi> obſerue firſt a particular act which muſt follow the generall <hi>preaching of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell;</hi> this expreſſed by the words, <hi>This done,</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenth verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>precious ointment,</hi> in the tenth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a good worke,</hi> verſe 11. preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore other <hi>good workes,</hi> as before giuing to the <hi>poore,</hi> The poore ye haue alwayes, me ye haue not <hi>alwayes;</hi> verſe 12. commended not only for the <hi>excellencie</hi> of the act, but the <hi>opportunitie</hi> of the time, In that ſhe powred this <hi>ointment</hi> on my body, ſhe did it for my <hi>buriall.</hi> Our Sauiour ioyneth, This Goſpell ſhall bee preached, and this. Secondly, the <hi>Author</hi> or <hi>Actor</hi> of this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14038:9"/>
               <hi>deed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math.
16.7.</note> this <hi>woman, Matthew</hi> ſayes no more, I here came vnto him a woman hauing an <hi>Alablaſter</hi> box, <hi>Marke</hi> ſaith no more<note n="*" place="margin">Mark. 14.4.</note> then <hi>Mathew,</hi> Saint<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ames this
<hi>woman. Mary</hi> tooke a pound of ointment; A bleſſed <hi>woman,</hi> as bleſſed as euer any, but onely <hi>ſhee</hi> whom all
<hi>generations</hi> ſhall call <hi>bleſſed.</hi> This woman,
<hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of her <hi>name, ornament</hi> of her <hi>Tribe,</hi> the
<hi>glory</hi> of her <hi>ſex,</hi> admitted to annoynt the <hi>head</hi> of our Sauiour: <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> the greateſt of the ſonnes of
<hi>women,</hi> not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to performe ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this <hi>woman,</hi> he baptiſed with <hi>water,</hi> ſhe annoints with <hi>oile, baptiſme common</hi> to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> people, <hi>vnction</hi> annointing of the
<hi>head,</hi> proper to the <hi>King</hi> the head of the people, this
<hi>woman</hi> did this, ſhe <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> the King of <hi>Kings,</hi> therefore our Sauiour tooke ſo gracious <hi>notice</hi> of it, <hi>this that this woman.</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>memoriall</hi> hereof, <hi>this that this woman hath done,</hi> ſhall be told in <hi>memoriall</hi> of her.
<hi>Maries</hi> memory is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by the
<hi>Church,</hi> by the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> by the <hi>Saints</hi> in all ages, ſooner <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> looſe their <hi>ſtations, ſunne</hi> and <hi>moone</hi> their <hi>motions, winter</hi> and
<hi>ſummer</hi> their <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> all the world ſhall ſooner vaniſh, and the frame of <hi>nature</hi> periſh then this
<hi>memoriall</hi> faile to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</hi> among the <hi>poſterities,</hi> this that this woman hath done, ſhall be told for a memoriall of her.
<hi>Laſtly,</hi> it ſhall be <hi>whereſoeuer,</hi> in euery
<hi>place</hi> where the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is <hi>read,</hi> or
<hi>heard,</hi> or <hi>preached, Maries memory</hi> followes our
<hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> as the <hi>marigold</hi> the <hi>ſunne: Mary</hi> that followed <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>feaſt</hi> of the <hi>Phariſie,</hi> to the <hi>houſe</hi> of the <hi>Leper,</hi> to the <hi>graue</hi> of
<hi>Lazarus,</hi> to the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> to the <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> to the
<hi>Garden,</hi> to <hi>Galile,</hi> now followes our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ouer all the <hi>world,</hi> for whereſoeuer the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is preached. You ſee here be no leſſe then ſeauen <hi>particulers,</hi> a whole
<hi>weeks worke,</hi> nay more a <hi>iourney</hi> ouer all the <hi>whole world.</hi> This is onely the <hi>comfort,</hi> as the <hi>wiſemen</hi> were lead by the <hi>light</hi> of a <hi>ſtarre,</hi> ſo we ſhall go by the
<hi>light</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> And to <hi>ſettle</hi> your
<hi>attentions,</hi> I beganne at the marke of my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14038:9"/>meditations, beginning as S. <hi>Marke</hi> beginnes his firſt chapter, The Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, whereſoeuer this Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nomen Euangelij nomen gaudij,</hi> ſaith the
<hi>gloſſe,</hi> the name of <hi>Goſpell</hi> is a name of
<hi>gladneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Gloſſe.</hi>
               </note> ſweete is this <hi>name,</hi> and the Saints <hi>loue it well.</hi> The name of <hi>Law</hi> was <hi>ſtrange,</hi> a <hi>name</hi> not ſo much as knowne to the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the time of <hi>Homer,</hi> as
<hi>Ioſephus</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ioſeph. contra Appion. lib.
<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> againſt <hi>Appion</hi> obſerueth that the word
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not ſo much as once vſed in all the writings of
<hi>Homer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scapula pag. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> but the name
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Budeus</hi> obſerues is found in <hi>Homer, Euripides,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtophanes,</hi> and <hi>Atheneus,</hi> and
<hi>Plutarch,</hi> wherein we ſee as neither the <hi>Iewes</hi> Law, no nor the name of it, was knowne a long time to the <hi>Gretians,</hi> ſo the name of <hi>Goſpell</hi> before the <hi>Goſpell</hi> was known to the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; a name vſed for <hi>glad-tidings</hi> among the Gentiles, as if it were moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the light of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> the 70. <hi>Interpreters</hi> vſe it as oft as they meete with
<hi>Baſar</hi> or <hi>Beſora</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to deliuer a meſſage, or be a Meſſenger. Saint<note n="a" place="margin">Luk.
1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> tells vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, many tooke in hand to write this <hi>Goſpell.</hi> And <hi>Theophilact</hi> vpon thoſe words<note n="b" place="margin">Theoph. in <hi>1.</hi> Luke.</note> ſaith <hi>attentarunt quidem Pſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doapoſtols, non perfecerunt: Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> tells vs the <hi>Tatiani</hi> had a Goſpell <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Egiptios:</hi> and
<hi>Epiphanius</hi> that ſome had a <hi>Goſpell ſecundum Hebraeos. Gnoſtickes</hi> had the Goſpell of <hi>Philip,</hi> and the
<hi>Maniches</hi> the Goſpell of <hi>Thomas,</hi> and others the Goſpell of
<hi>Matthias:</hi> But <hi>Baſilides</hi> of all others as Saint
<hi>Hierome</hi> obſerues was the moſt <hi>bold</hi> and
<hi>blaſphemous,</hi> that durſt write a <hi>booke</hi> and entitle it his
<hi>Goſpell.</hi> But as all the <hi>Fathers</hi> confuted thoſe
<hi>hereſies,</hi> and ſtopped the mouthes of theſe blaſphemies, ſo eſpecially <hi>Irenaeus</hi> by the foure windes, Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> out of <hi>Zacharies</hi> viſion<note n="c" place="margin">Zach. 6.1.</note> by the foure Chariots, and Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> out of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion<note n="d" place="margin">Ezek. 1.6.</note> by the foure Cherubins, ſhew there be no more but foure <hi>Euangeliſts,</hi> and theſe foure to concurre to one <hi>quatuor Euangelia eſſe vnum Euangelium, et ſi aliud at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14038:10"/>aliud ob perſonaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> differentiam, vnum tamen ob eorum quae loquuntur conſonantiam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi> the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is therefore the glad-tidings of God to
<hi>ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. tom. <hi>4.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Gal.</note> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ioyfull meſſage that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> came into the <hi>world</hi> to ſaue <hi>ſinners:</hi> the Law was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.7.</note> but the Goſpell <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Law of <hi>death</hi> was turned into the Goſpell of <hi>life,</hi> and therefore was <hi>Moſes</hi> in the transfiguration with Chriſt, becauſe the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was
<hi>transfigured</hi> by the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Now the Goſpell doth <hi>conſider Chriſt</hi> eſpecially either as hee was
<hi>corpus carnis</hi> in his incarnation, in the veile of fleſh or as
<hi>corpus mortis,</hi> in his Paſſion as hee was in the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, or as <hi>primitiae reſurrectionis,</hi> in his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and triumph ouer death, and as in all other of Chriſt his paſſages, ſo eſpecially in theſe the Goſpell is the glad-tidings: it was glad-tiding in his birth, when the Meſſenger was an Angell, the meſſage a Goſpell, but when the Sauiour of men and Angells deliuers a Goſpell much more it is glad-tidings. So is it here where our Sauiour the Authour of the Goſpell deliuers a Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. <hi>This Goſpell:</hi> and what this Goſpell is is expreſſed in the ſecond verſe, it is the crucifying of Chriſt, in the twelfth verſe the buriall and reſurrection of Chriſt and indeed theſe of all other, are the glad-tidings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, for the Paſſion and reſurrection of Chriſt are the lines, that the Patriarches and Prophets beheld by the perſpectiue of faith in the beautifull peeces of Gods promiſes, theſe aboue all, bee the glad-tidings, euen this Goſpell of Chriſts death and triumph ouer death: the Angells in Chriſts reſurrection told the women <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.6. Remember how he ſpake vnto you in <hi>Galile,</hi> the ſonne of man ſhall be deliuered into the hands of ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.6.</note> and be crucified, and the third day riſe againe. Indeed this was the Goſpell, and this Goſpell he eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally taught his Diſciples, and hee taught his Goſpell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in <hi>Galile,</hi> when he came into <hi>Galile</hi> hee taught
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14038:10"/>his Diſciples the ſonne of man ſhall bee deliuered and killed, and riſe the third day, <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.31.<note place="margin">Math.
9.31.</note> while they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in <hi>Galile</hi> he taught his Diſciples the ſonne of man, ſhall be betraied into the hands of men, they ſhall kill him and be ſhall be raiſed againe the third day,<note place="margin">Math.
17.22.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 17.22. when he came towards <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from <hi>Galile,</hi> he taught them this, the Sauiour of man ſhall bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the Gentiles, ſhall bee crucified and the third day ſhall riſe againe, <hi>Math.</hi> 20.19. going to <hi>Galile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.19.</note> in <hi>Galile,</hi> throughout
<hi>Galile,</hi> comming out of <hi>Galile</hi> hee taught his Diſciples his Paſſion and reſurrection. <hi>Galile</hi> as <hi>Ierome</hi> and others, ſignifieth <hi>tranſmigrationem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierom. interp. Nom. Heb.</note> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture a tranſmigration. It was the Goſpell of
<hi>Galile,</hi> of his tranſmigration, he did teach this Goſpell of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration, in the Land of tranſmigration, it was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration from life to death by his Paſſion, from death to life by his reſurrection. The whole Goſpell is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle ſent from God ſaith
<hi>Auſtin, Euangelium Dei, epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la de caelo miſſa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> And it repreſenteth Chriſt vnto vs
<hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantem, docentem, mira patrantem dira patientem,</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, teaching, accompliſhing wonderfull ſuffering ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull things,<note place="margin">Baſill.</note> as <hi>Baſill</hi> ſpeakes this death the miniſtery of our life, the life of man, but death of ſinne, death of Sathan, in the death of our Sauiour. This is a Goſpell of glad-tidings, and is it glad tidings? to heare that ſuch a perſon as the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Math. 13.99.</note> 
               <hi>Mark.</hi> 15.39 ſuffered ſuch a Paſſion as the curſe of the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15. by ſo great a compaſſion, as to doe it for his enemies.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> That in his birth he was placed among beaſts, then tempted by Deuills, then perſecuted by Tyrants, then condemned by murtherers, then crucified among theeues, and thus he did liue, thus he did die. To heare him contemned for his progeny, a Carpenters ſonne; for his Prouince, a <hi>Galilean;</hi> for his profeſſion, a Samaritan; his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Law breakers, his doctrine treaſon, ſeducing the people, his miracles impoſtures, caſting out Deuils by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14038:11"/>
               <hi>Beelſebub,</hi> his company Publicans and ſinners, for his whole life breaking the Sabbaoth, a bibber of wine, working by the Deuill, poſſeſſed with the Deuill: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee muſt die. If it bee glad-tidings? to heare of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Nazianz.</note> as <hi>Nazianzene</hi> collects, them of the ſtripes, and ſcoffings, and ſpittings, and thornes, and croſſe, and nailes, and ſpeare, and ſweate, and bloud, and wounds, and diſtresfull crie, and horrid death: to heare and ſee this prodigious Tragedy, in a theatre of dead mens bones, couered ouer with ruth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full darkeneſſe, Angells, Diuells, rockes, graues, the whole vniuers and Creature concurring to this ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, onely the ſunne abſenting, abhorring to ſee ſuch a death,<note place="margin">Alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus.</note> 
               <hi>Supplicium quo nullum maius, opprobrium quo nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vilius,</hi> the graue and hell, yelling out their griefe, for the wonder of our redemption, by this wofull paſſion.</p>
            <p>If this be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> glad tidings? as who dare deny it to be, for if <hi>Appian</hi> writing of the murther of <hi>Tully</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed his letter, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Carrying good newes to Anthory:</hi> then how glad, how good, thoſe tidings of the death of Chriſt; If it bee glad-tidings, as who can deny it to be? vnleſſe they bee enemies to the croſſe of Chriſt, and ſeeke to euacuate the croſſe of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17. whereas Chriſt hath reconciled all things by his croſſe, <hi>Coloſſ</hi> 1.20. and ſhine enmity by his body on the croſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.16. and the power of God is the preaching of the croſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. The croſſe being <hi>non patibutum Patientis, ſed tribunal Trium phantiss,</hi> as <hi>Ierome</hi> calles it: If in the ſtormy winter of his death,<note place="margin">Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſuch life, then what luſtre, what glory, what beautie, what life of life, in the ſpring of life. The croſſe of Chriſt is the onely knowledge of a Chriſt an, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 2.2. The excellencie of his knowledge, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. The glorie of his knowledge, <hi>Gal.</hi>
6.14. Which made the Apoſtle crie out God forbid, that I ſhould glorie in any thing but in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. But
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14038:11"/>looke how farre life ſurpaſſeth death, ſo farre is the ioy of the Reſurrection aboue the Paſſion, no tongue can expreſſe this noble act of the Lord his bleſſed and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Reſurrection, <hi>Mori dignatus eſt ex voluntate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> 
               <hi>ſed reſurrexit ex poteſtate,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian;</hi> when neither bowells of the earth, nor ligament of the graue, nor ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of death, nor power of hell, able to containe him, but that Chriſt is riſen againe, Chriſt is riſen from the dead, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he beſt time of the whole yeere, the time of the great Paſſouer, firſt day of the weeke, beſt day of the yeere, firſt houre of the day, at dawning of the daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie day, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.1. riſing of the ſunne, <hi>Mark.</hi>
16.1. early in the morning, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1. early while it was dark,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 20.1. <hi>Oritus ex alto, oriens ex imo,</hi> hee that was the reſurrection and life, roſe by his reſurrection vnto life, and became the firſt fruites of the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. firſt begotten of the dead, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.5. firſt borne of the dead, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi>
1.18. firſt of thoſe that did ariſe from the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.23. Here is glory, and ioy, and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidings, and if euer the ſoules of the Saints and ſeruants of God, were tranſported out of their bodily ſenſes, it ſhould be at this Goſpell that I bring vnto you of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidings, of great ioy that ſhall bee to all people, that Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſleepe; Chriſt is riſen from the dead, and now dieth no more, Chriſt is riſen from the dead, death where is thy ſting? graue where is thy victorie? thankes be giuen vnto God, who hath giuen vs victorie by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. It may ſeeme to be collected, that this Goſpell, is the Goſpell of the reſurrection not only in 32. verſ. <hi>when I am riſen, I will go before you into Galile:</hi> but more manifeſtly out of the 12. verſ. <hi>In that ſhee pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this ointment on my body, ſhe did it for my buriall:</hi> why was the body annointed for the buriall, but in reſpect of the reſurrection of the body? Saint <hi>Paul</hi> asketh the queſtion, why are they baptized for the dead,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> if no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14038:12"/>reſurrection of the dead? why an annointing of Chriſts body, vnleſſe becauſe of the reſurrection of his body?
<hi>Reſurrectio Chriſti complementum omnium promiſſionum,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquia.</note> without which, no promiſe performed, no propheſie fulfilled, no myſterie reuealed, no body redeemed from the power of death, no ſoule could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Goſpell of life; Chriſt tooke vpon him the name of the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Ioh.
11.25.</note> 
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.25. gaue no ſigne but of the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Math. 12 39.</note> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 12.39. ſhewed his power, wrought our righteouſneſſe, by no meanes ſo euidently as by the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Rom 4.25.</note>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. taught his Diſciples, no doctrine ſo frequently, in 6. Chapters in <hi>Mathew,</hi> in 5. <hi>Marke,</hi> in 4. in <hi>Luke</hi> often in <hi>Iohn,</hi> mention of his reſurrection: ſo that eſpecially this Goſpell is the Goſpell of Chriſts reſurrection from which root ariſeth this fruitfull branch of doctune:<note place="margin">Doct.</note> The reſurrection of Chriſt is the moſt glad-tiding, of the Goſpell, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth in it the ſumme of the whole Goſpell. So S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Reſurrectio Chriſts tota fides Chriſtianorum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt is the whole faith of Chriſtians: So <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note>
               <hi>vis Euangelij Epitomen, en reſurrectionem,</hi> wilt thou haue an Epitome of all the Goſpell, behold the reſurrection:<note place="margin">Hilary.</note> So <hi>Hilary, Reſurrectionis teſtimonium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium munus Apoſtolorum,</hi> The teſtimonie of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is the chiefe office of the Apoſtles. The reaſons of this doctrine are many, without this all the myſteries of our redemption were vaine: Pleaſe but to walke into the ſpring Garden of the reſurrection the 15. of the 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> where the Apoſtle ſheweth that if it were not for the reſurrection of Chriſt that are already a ſleep are periſhed,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> they that are aliue, are in their ſinnes, and therefore dead, twiſe telleth them your faith vaine, our preaching vaine, and wee and you of all men moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, Hearers and Preachers, and liuing, &amp; dead, and all miſerable. Death ſhould wound vs vnto death, the graue ſhut her mouth vpon vs, the deuouring throate of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14038:12"/>an open Sepulchre cloſe her iawes vpon vs: our portion onely in this life, and we no better then the life of beaſts, temples, and Bibles, and faith, and hope, and heauen, and all in vaine, were it not for the reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead. Againe the reſurrection of Chriſt in that one act comprehendeth all the acts of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; here is Chriſts incarnation, hee tooke fleſh againe vpon him, here is his conception as before a virgine mother, ſo here a virgine ſepulchre, here is his baptiſme, as he came out of the waters, ſo now hee commeth out of the earth, as in the temptation after fourtie daies hee came from the wilderneſſe, ſo hereafter fourtie houres he commeth into the world, here is his tranſmigration, whereby he is tranſlated from death to life. In his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection the confluence of all his miracles, hee that gaue ſight to the blinde, openeth his owne eies, and eares to the deafe, openeth his owne eares, and ſpeech to the dumbe, openeth his owne mouth, he that badde the lame man ariſe and walke, ariſeth from death and walketh, and herein worketh the greateſt miracle that euer hee did: <hi>Non ſuſcitauit alterum ſed ſe ſeipſum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>nec ſuſcitatioſed reſurrectio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> Hee raiſed not vp another but himſelfe, and it was not paſſiuely to bee raiſed by another power, but actiuely by his owne, not a raiſing but a riſing. So that this of all others is the ſumme of the Goſpell, neuer glad-tidings till now, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo glad, ſo good-tidings as now,<note place="margin">Bona:</note> 
               <hi>In naſcendo contulit conſortium naturae, in patiendo beneficium gratiae, in reſurgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do complementum gloriae:</hi> In his birth hee conferred the fellowſhip of nature, in death, the benefit of grace, in riſing, complement of glory, ſaith <hi>Bonauenture.</hi> Herein, onely herein he brought <hi>defunctis vitam, peccatoribus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, Sanctis gloriam:</hi> Life to the dead, pardon to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, glory to Saints, as
<hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh. Therefore we reioyce, and hereby our ioy ſhall bee full: <hi>Surrexit Chriſtus exultet vniuerſus mundus,</hi> The ioy of this time,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14038:13"/>like that of the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the
<hi>Canticles,</hi> which may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Chriſts reſurrection;
<hi>Ariſe my Loue, my faire one, the winter is paſt, the raine is oner and gone, the flowers appeare in the earth, the time of the ſinging of birds is come, the voice of the Turtle is heard in our Land, the Figge-tree putteth forth her greene figges, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ines with their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grapes yeeld a good ſmell: Ariſe, my Loue, my Doue, my Faire one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>and come away Exultet vniuerſus mundus,</hi> Let the world reioyce and all that are therein. The <hi>righteous branch</hi> of the root of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> hath reflouriſhed, the
<hi>Lion</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> is awakened, our <hi>Phenix</hi> is riſen from his owne aſhes, our <hi>Eagle</hi> renewed his bill, our
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> is brought out of <hi>priſon,</hi> our <hi>Sampſon</hi> hath carried away the gates of <hi>Aſſah,</hi> our <hi>Mordecai</hi> is exalted, our <hi>Daniel</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the denne, our <hi>Ionas</hi> is caſt vp by the whale, our <hi>Lazarus</hi> reſtored to life, our
<hi>Glory,</hi> our <hi>Goſpell,</hi> our <hi>Glad tidings,</hi> our
<hi>Chriſt</hi> is riſen from the dead.</p>
            <p>Let vs then aboue all other <hi>meditations</hi> reioyce in the knowledge of the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> and eſpecially in the remembrance of the reſurrection of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſeeing that as the Goſpell is the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God to ſaluation, ſo the
<hi>reſurrection,</hi> of all other parts, hath manifeſted the power of our
<hi>redemption,</hi> from the <hi>graue,</hi> from <hi>ſinne,</hi> from
<hi>death,</hi> from the <hi>Deuill.</hi> Let vs reioyce in the
<hi>reſurrection</hi> of our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur,</hi> ſeeing by this hee ſhall raiſe our vile bodies, to bee like his <hi>glorious body.</hi> Let vs with all care embrace <hi>this faith,</hi> ſeeing the bright <hi>morning ſtarre</hi> which was dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>death,</hi> hath recouered <hi>light,</hi> let vs be ſure he will bring vs out of
<hi>darkneſſe</hi> into the light of his <hi>countenance. Abraham</hi> ſaw the day of <hi>Chriſts birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eg. Mor.</note>
               <hi>Eſay</hi> fore ſaw the day of <hi>Chriſts death, Iob</hi> ſaw the day his <hi>dunghill.</hi> Let vs beginne the firſt reſurrection from
<hi>ſinne</hi> to <hi>grace,</hi> that wee may be raiſed from
<hi>nature</hi> to <hi>glory.</hi> Of all the Feaſts of the whole
<hi>Church</hi> in the whole <hi>yeere,</hi> wee haue none
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14038:13"/>like this: the <hi>Church</hi> inioyneth the reſt, <hi>Scripture</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands this: <hi>S. Paul</hi> giues an iniunction for celebrating of <hi>Eaſter;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> is offered for vs,<note place="margin">1 Cor.
5.7.</note> let vs keepe the <hi>Feaſt,</hi> our <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> for vs let vs, <hi>Noſtrum, Nobis, Nos. Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> indeed, as hee was <hi>offered,</hi> and our <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> as he was
<hi>raiſed,</hi> paſſing from death to life: Let vs then keepe this
<hi>Feaſt. Pauls</hi> iniunction is an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> for this
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> of this <hi>Feaſt.</hi> All the <hi>Saints</hi> on earth through the Chriſtian world, keepe this Feaſt, as their ioy and
<hi>Iubile:</hi> All the <hi>Angels</hi> in heauen (ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi>) obſerue the ſame;<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
               <hi>Ipſi Angeli eius gaudia Paſchata agunt in coeleſtibus.</hi> Let vs then obſerue theſe
<hi>ſolemnities,</hi> in the meditation of this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> with all reuerence to this <hi>glad tidings</hi> of <hi>Chriſts reſurrection.</hi> Let vs keepe the feaſt, not with old <hi>leauen,</hi> not with the old
<hi>leauen</hi> of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> but with the
<hi>vnleauened bread</hi> of <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> and <hi>truth.</hi> Let the
<hi>dead</hi> burie their <hi>dead;</hi> let vs bring forth ſome
<hi>fruits</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to ariſe from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God. <hi>Epicures, Baſilidians, Sadduces, Saturnians,</hi> denie the <hi>truth</hi> of Chriſts <hi>reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> let not vs denie the <hi>power.</hi> Which we doe if wee bring not forth the fruits of the
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> if we caſt not off the <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>death</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe.</hi> Chriſt appeared firſt to <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> and ſent her to be the firſt <hi>meſſenger</hi> to
<hi>Peter;</hi> Chriſt to <hi>Magdalen, Magdalen</hi> to <hi>Peter, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> the <hi>greateſt ſinner</hi> among <hi>women, Peter</hi> the
<hi>greatest ſinner</hi> among <hi>men; Magdalen</hi> to <hi>Peter, Magdalen</hi> clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of <hi>ſeuen Deuils,</hi> ſent to <hi>Peter</hi> pardoned of <hi>three deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als.</hi> Let <hi>Magdalen</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> preach this to you, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and <hi>this day if ye will heare his voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 95.7.</note>
               <hi>harden not your hearts.</hi> Beloued, hee that is riſen from the
<hi>graue,</hi> is not riſen in all your <hi>hearts;</hi> with the
<hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> yee haue laid a <hi>ſtone,</hi> and the <hi>Deuill</hi> he hath laid the <hi>watch,</hi> and that heauy graue ſtone of
<hi>ſinne</hi> ſealed <hi>downe,</hi> preſſeth downe ſoules: few will be <hi>raiſed,</hi> few ſhall bee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14038:14"/>
               <hi>ſaued.</hi> The <hi>hypocrite</hi> dares not riſe, hee hath ſo many <hi>ſhapes,</hi> he feareth God will not know him, if he meet him. The <hi>harlot</hi> cannot riſe, ſhee is a dead ſoule in a <hi>painted Sepulchre.</hi> The <hi>drunkard</hi> would riſe, but hath neither <hi>hand</hi> nor <hi>foot</hi> to help himſelfe, the earths
<hi>monſter,</hi> and his owne <hi>murtherer.</hi> The <hi>Gallant</hi> like
<hi>Lazarus</hi> in the graue, <hi>is faſt bound, is cloſe priſoner to his owne clothes.</hi> The <hi>Vſurer</hi> is <hi>Iaylor</hi> to other mens
<hi>bonds,</hi> and <hi>bondſlaue</hi> to his owne <hi>money.</hi> The
<hi>Courtier</hi> of all other is moſt <hi>carefull</hi> to riſe, yet no man ſleepes <hi>longer,</hi> either fettered with <hi>hopes,</hi> or enſnared by <hi>fancie,</hi> or <hi>bewitched</hi> by <hi>fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur,</hi> but beginning with falſe <hi>footing,</hi> fals, and lies by it. The plaine
<hi>Country man</hi> riſeth vp early, goeth late to bed, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the bread of
<hi>carefulneſſe,</hi> obſerueth how dearth <hi>ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,</hi> but for other <hi>riſing,</hi> he beleeues it is enough if hee ſhall riſe at the laſt day. The <hi>Citizen,</hi> of all other is moſt <hi>likely</hi> to ariſe, the <hi>Citie</hi> being the Sea into which all the <hi>freſh riuers</hi> runne, though many <hi>ſhips</hi> here ſuffer ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke. The <hi>Citizen</hi> is willing to <hi>riſe,</hi> for it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble how he ſhould <hi>ſleepe,</hi> and as worthy to riſe as any; he is the States <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> and the Lands <hi>Pillar,</hi> and ſure the
<hi>Citizens</hi> riſing would be <hi>bleſſed</hi> if hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ſtaires</hi> were not <hi>crooked.</hi> We our ſelues that preach the
<hi>reſurrection,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not riſe, becauſe we will not heare our
<hi>ſelues.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> as well as <hi>Church-yard</hi> is full of <hi>dead bodies:</hi> willingly would many of vs riſe, though by <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: others would riſe, but they haue no
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> to put them into the <hi>Poole:</hi> others are riſen, and worſe then <hi>Magdalen,</hi> neuer preached ſince their
<hi>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> Beloued, theſe are not the fruits of the
<hi>Goſpell,</hi> not the fruits of the <hi>reſurrection.</hi> I am no
<hi>Satyre,</hi> nor this place a <hi>Paſquill:</hi> I acknowledge many, and many bleſſed <hi>ſeruants</hi> of God, to be <hi>fruitfull</hi> in this
<hi>doctrine,</hi> in <hi>Church, Court, Citie, Countrey:</hi> yet be there not in this <hi>Auditorie,</hi> that would be more heartily <hi>inflamed</hi> with ſome other <hi>Goſpell</hi> then this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſome other doctrine
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14038:14"/>then this of the <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iz <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would willingly heare this Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſed,
<hi>Owe noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to any man but loue:</hi> and ſome poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Creditors</hi> this T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vrged, <hi>The good man is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcifull, and lendeth.</hi> Some grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lawyers deſire to heare this Text preſſed, <hi>The Law is good, if a man vſe it lawfully,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.8. but ſome poore <hi>Clients</hi> this Text opened, <hi>Brethren, there is vtterly a fault among you, that yee goe to law one with another,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor</hi> 6.7. The <hi>Glutton</hi> would no Text but this, <hi>Goe eat of the fat, and drinke of the ſweet, Nehemiah</hi> 8.10. The <hi>I ſurer</hi> none but this Text, <hi>A wiſe man put out his Talents to vſe, Mat.</hi> 25.14. The <hi>Country man</hi> would heare the <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> compared to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> fat and leane kine, the one <hi>deuouring</hi> the other. The <hi>Citizen</hi> and <hi>Countrey man</hi> would heare that Chriſt was firſt perſecuted by the <hi>Court,</hi> at his <hi>birth</hi> by <hi>Herod</hi> and his Court, at his <hi>death</hi> by <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>late</hi> and his Court. Of all Texts, there is one tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all in Countrey and City. Yet in the meane time the poore
<hi>Miniſter</hi> hath found the <hi>Text,</hi> and preached it, though it
<hi>takes no ſucceſſe,</hi> and it is a <hi>Text</hi> to be taught all, and his Text is <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.22.<note place="margin">Deut. 14 22.</note>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt truly tithe of all thy increaſe.</hi> And he is bound to
<hi>preach</hi> this, for how can he preach vnleſſe he be maintained? and bound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee <hi>heareth God curſe</hi> where man <hi>denieth tithe.</hi> Reade when you come home, with horrour,<note place="margin">Mal.
3.8:</note> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Will a man rob God? yet yee haue robbed mee, ſaith the Lord.</hi> But yee ſay, Wherein haue wee robbed thee? His anſwer is, <hi>In tithes and offerings, therefore yee are curſed with a curſe.</hi> But I forget my ſelfe. Chriſts ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the reſurrection was <hi>Peace be vnto you,</hi> and I bring to you a
<hi>Goſpell of peace. Ariſe therefore thou that ſleepeſt, if Chriſt ſhall giue thee life,</hi> let not <hi>Adams</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Achans</hi> wedge, <hi>Eſaus</hi> broth, <hi>Babylons</hi> cuppe, <hi>Iudas</hi> ſoppe, betray thee; the <hi>ſnares</hi> of Sathan, <hi>fetters</hi> of the fleſh,
<hi>chambers</hi> of death, <hi>workes</hi> of darkneſſe, <hi>chaines</hi> of hell, enthrall thee; ariſe by Chriſt, to Chriſt, with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14038:15"/>Chriſt, as if yee had embraced this Goſpell of Chriſt, ſeeing this Goſpell is a preached Goſpell. My ſecond paſſage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preaching</hi> is the ordinary meanes to worke beleeuing. It is the <hi>Trumpet</hi> of <hi>Eſay,</hi> the <hi>Cymball</hi> of
<hi>Dauid,</hi> the ſound of <hi>Aarons bels</hi> in the <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> the <hi>ſauour</hi> of life vnto life vnto them that beleeue. It is a
<hi>ſpeech</hi> to men to <hi>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, exhortation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>comfort,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.3. Preaching is the <hi>ceſterne</hi> to conuay life and beleefe to the ſoule, the <hi>knife</hi> to diuide the <hi>Scripture,</hi> the <hi>key</hi> of the Kingdome of heauen,<note place="margin">Ier 23.29. Rom. 1.16. Ier. 23.29. Eſay
55.11. Eph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 6.17. Heb. 4.12.</note> a <hi>fire, Ier.</hi> 23.29. a
<hi>power, Rom.</hi> 1.16. a <hi>ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Ier.</hi> 23.29. a <hi>ſhower, Eſay</hi> 55.11. a <hi>ſword,</hi> euen the ſword of the <hi>ſpirit, Epheſ.</hi> 6.17. A <hi>ſword</hi> ſharper then a two-edged ſword,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. The <hi>Proclamation</hi> which the Lord hath vſed by the mouth of all his <hi>holy Prophets</hi> ſince the world beganne, whereby God hath euer ſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a <hi>vocation</hi> of men, to deale betwixt <hi>God and man,</hi> whoſe <hi>preaching</hi> in their <hi>miniſterie</hi> is aboue all other <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,</hi> as the <hi>Schooles</hi> obſerue,<note place="margin">Aquin. All<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt.</note> 
               <hi>Dicere infra, Docere circa, Predicare ſupra:</hi> Wee ſpeake of things <hi>beneath</hi> vs, our teaching is of thoſe things <hi>about</hi> vs, but preaching is of things <hi>aboue</hi> vs. In the <hi>Primitiue world</hi> the firſt borne was the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and
<hi>Preacher</hi> to the familie. Before the <hi>Floud, Enoch</hi> a Preacher of <hi>Righteouſneſſe, Iude</hi> 14. At the <hi>Floud, Noah</hi> a Preacher of <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. Before the Law,
<hi>Melchiſedecke</hi> a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prieſt, Gen.</hi> 14.18. In the Law, <hi>Salomon</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Preacher, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 1.1. The Lord neuer intended his word ſhould be laid vp only as the
<hi>Tables</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the <hi>ſword</hi> of
<hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> or the Kings <hi>Treaſurie</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> but ordained an <hi>Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiaſticall Hierarchie</hi> for his <hi>Church</hi> by a <hi>Tribe</hi> of his <hi>chuſing,</hi> to breake the bread of life to his <hi>choſen. Aaron</hi> ſo honored with the <hi>Miter, Cenſor, Altar, Crowne, royall roabes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut 33.10.</note> and
<hi>miraculous rod,</hi> he and his Tribe were inioyned by God to teach
<hi>Iacob</hi> his iudgements, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his Lawes, <hi>Deut.</hi>
33.10. The very forme of our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14038:15"/>preaching was practiſed by the
<hi>Leuites</hi> vnder the Law, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 8. verſe 2. The
<hi>meeting</hi> of the Congregation, verſe 3. <hi>Place</hi> in the ſtreet neere the water gate, 4. <hi>Eſra</hi> the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſtood in a
<hi>Pulpit</hi> made of wood, 6. His <hi>Praier</hi> before Sermon, the Prophets <hi>Amen,</hi> 5. His <hi>opening the booke,</hi> 8. His reading the
<hi>Text,</hi> opening the <hi>meaning,</hi> giuing the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> cauſing them to vnderſtand. Thus <hi>preaching</hi> vnder the <hi>Law.</hi> Vnder the <hi>Goſpell</hi> it was the miniſterie of
<hi>reconciliation,</hi> the <hi>promulgation</hi> of the <hi>glad tidings</hi> of the Goſpell, and the imploying of the <hi>Talent</hi> God beſtoweth,
<hi>Talentum quod creditum, non quod inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Lirinenſis;</hi> A <hi>Talent</hi> receiued, not deuiſed:<note place="margin">Lirinenſ.</note> Then by <hi>preaching hearing,</hi> by
<hi>hearing faith</hi> obtained. Neuer was there ſo large a
<hi>Commiſſion</hi> granted, as the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of preaching,
<hi>Goe into all Nations Matt.</hi> 28.19. And as large was the execution, for they preached in <hi>euery City, Acts</hi> 15.21. in <hi>euery Church, Acts</hi> 19.23. in <hi>euery place, Mark,</hi> 16.20. at <hi>euery time,</hi> in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. to <hi>euery creature</hi> vnder heauen, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. The Goſpell was thus generally prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and to the <hi>end of the world</hi> muſt be preached. From which word preached, as out of a <hi>fountaine,</hi> ariſeth this ſtreame of Doctrine: <hi>The preaching of the Goſpell is both the eſpeciall ordinance, and great bleſſing of God.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe it is a <hi>light</hi> to them that ſit in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and a <hi>light</hi> that God hath appointed to bee carried before his people.
<hi>A light indeede,</hi> to them that ſate in <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> where the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of
<hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and
<hi>ſhadow</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> did ouerwhelme them. There neuer was ſo great <hi>miſerie</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as when no <hi>Prophet</hi> to teach them. Three eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall remarkable wants, all harbingers of woe to
<hi>Iſrael:</hi> No <hi>Smith</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
13.19. No <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Iſrael, Iudges</hi> 18.1. No <hi>Prieſt</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.3. the <hi>laſt</hi> of all the
<hi>reſt</hi> moſt <hi>miſerable.</hi> As <hi>dolefull,</hi> as
<hi>fearfull,</hi> is <hi>Dauids</hi> complaint of that time, <hi>Wee ſee no tokens, there
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14038:16"/>is no Prophet more, no man of God in the Land, no man that vnderſtandeth any more,</hi> no <hi>teaching,</hi> no
<hi>Law,</hi> no <hi>peace,</hi> no <hi>God</hi> among them, becauſe no
<hi>Prieſt</hi> among them. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer. Ili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> All things <hi>ouerthwart, declining, crooked,</hi> nay
<hi>curſed.</hi> The <hi>word</hi> therefore is a <hi>light</hi> vnto our
<hi>feet,</hi> and a <hi>lampe</hi> to our <hi>paths,</hi> and the
<hi>preaching</hi> of this <hi>word</hi> ſo neceſſary, that as without
<hi>hearing</hi> no <hi>beleeuing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 10.14.</note> ſo no <hi>hearing</hi> without <hi>preaching, Rom.</hi> 10 14. And where no
<hi>preaching,</hi> the people periſh, <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.18. I denie not that
<hi>reading</hi> is a <hi>bleſſed</hi> exerciſe,<note place="margin">Reu.
1.3.</note> and bleſſed is he that readeth, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.3. A great part of <hi>S. Auſtins</hi> conuerſion is imputed to his reading of a place of <hi>Scripture:</hi> but ſure I am, that the <hi>Promiſe</hi> is annexed to <hi>preaching;</hi> and <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtin C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ</note> that by <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> preaching he was eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. So in his confeſſion to God may be collected: <hi>Ad cum Deus per te ducebar neſcius, vt ad te per cum ſciens ducerer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> It was <hi>preaching</hi> rather then <hi>baptizing,</hi> wherein our <hi>Sauiour</hi> was exerciſed,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 4.2. <hi>Fecit mira, dixit multa,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard;</hi> hee wrought <hi>miracles,</hi> hee ſpake <hi>Oracles.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> But as if hee had onely come to the world to
<hi>preach,</hi> he proclaimes himſelfe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18.19. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is vpon mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 4.18.</note>
               <hi>and hath anointed mee to preach, to preach the Goſpell to the poore, to preach deliuerance to the captiues, to preach the acceptable yeere of the Lord.</hi> In the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> they traueld, &amp; thirſted, &amp; hungered, &amp; laboured, &amp; ſweat, and bled, and died, and compaſſed ſea and land, for the obtaining of this <hi>Iewell;</hi> and in that <hi>Infancie</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> hauing found <hi>preaching,</hi> though as the <hi>Wiſe men</hi> Chriſt in the cratch, they adored it. The
<hi>Eccleſiaſticall Storie</hi> is plentifull herein, not to bring forth in this Sunſhine the <hi>ſacred Lampes</hi> burning in thoſe golden candleſtickes, <hi>Polycarpus, Ignatius,</hi> and <hi>Clemens,</hi> and thoſe many Diſciples of the Diſciples of the Lord. <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> records in his time holy mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, reading, preaching, an houre euery Sabaoth.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14038:16"/>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Tertull.</note> that all the meetings of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were celebrated with holy Sermons. The <hi>Councell of Mentz</hi> ordained that euery day of the Lord the word of the Lord ſhould be preached, &amp; at the length great was the multitude of the Preachers, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> deliuered euery where by <hi>preaching,</hi> as by the only means to bring
<hi>ſaluation.</hi> And ſure if any part of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> might haue beene deliuered ſufficiently without <hi>preaching,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of the
<hi>reſurrection</hi> might; for after our <hi>Sauiour</hi> had ſhewed himſelfe aliue by infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible proofes,<note place="margin">Act. 1.3.</note> as
<hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3. ſuch as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, prouing his <hi>reſurrection</hi> to all the
<hi>ſenſes;</hi> by the <hi>ſight,</hi> hee ſhewed, and they ſaw his
<hi>wounds;</hi> by <hi>hearing,</hi> he <hi>ſpake,</hi> they <hi>heard,</hi> Peace be vnto you; by <hi>taſting,</hi> they miniſtred, and he taſted
<hi>broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fiſh;</hi> by the <hi>touch, Thomas</hi> doubted, and the Lord conſtrained him to <hi>touch</hi> his <hi>wounds;</hi> by the
<hi>ſmell,</hi> the Lord <hi>breathed</hi> on them, and they receiued the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Nature</hi> ſeekes but to ſenſe, the fiue ſenſes fiue porches of <hi>Natures Palace.</hi> In euery ſenſe the
<hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of Chriſt proclaimed, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>this Goſpell muſt be preached.</hi> When no <hi>circumſtance</hi> of
<hi>time,</hi> or <hi>place,</hi> or <hi>perſon,</hi> vnmanifeſted,
<hi>appearing</hi> the day of his reſurrection early in the <hi>morning,</hi> late at <hi>night,</hi> both times of day; to the <hi>Diſciples abroad</hi> and in the <hi>houſe,</hi> both places; to <hi>Souldiers</hi> and
<hi>Apoſtles,</hi> both conditions; <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> both religions; <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> both ſexes; <hi>liuing</hi> and <hi>dead,</hi> both eſtates; when <hi>friends, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Diſciples, ſtrangers, Angels, Deuils,</hi> bare witneſſe, and <hi>graues</hi> opened their <hi>mouthes</hi> to proclaime this <hi>point,</hi> yet
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after the <hi>horrour</hi> of the <hi>Earth-quake, rolling</hi> the ſtone, <hi>ſeeing</hi> the clothes, <hi>hearing</hi> the Angell, <hi>witneſſe</hi> of the women, <hi>ſatisfying Thomas,</hi> eating, ſpeaking, walking, breathing on them, breaking bread with them,
<hi>bodily</hi> preſence 40. dayes among them, hauing beene ſeene to more then 500. at once, 11. <hi>Diſciples</hi> being
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14038:17"/>witneſſes of this, <hi>another</hi> muſt be added to be witneſſe to preach the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Act. 1.22.</note> not <hi>caeterorum tantum, ſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionis teſtem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> So neceſſarie is preaching the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> no <hi>Goſpell</hi> without preaching.</p>
            <p>Let vs then embrace the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Goſpell with
<hi>gladnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </note> as that which is able to <hi>ſaue our ſoules at the great day,</hi> the kingdome of
<hi>God,</hi> by the preaching of the <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi> is among vs, let him that hath an eare heare what the Spirit ſaith,<note place="margin">Hoſ.
8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Were the things of the Law honourable?</hi> Hoſ. 8.12. How much more ſhould the gracious word brought vnto vs, by the <hi>preaching</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> Was the ſecond perſon of the Trinitie called the
<hi>Word,</hi> and that Word made fleſh; and the third perſon the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> came downe in <hi>tongues of fire,</hi> and thoſe
<hi>tongues</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen to preach <hi>that word,</hi> how then ſhould our harts burne within vs, to <hi>enflame vs</hi> to the deſire of theſe
<hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things?</hi> It is much that <hi>Enoch</hi> and
<hi>Elias</hi> both <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> of all other were taken vp to
<hi>heauen,</hi> that <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> both Preachers, of all other were ſaued from the <hi>double</hi> deluge of <hi>fire</hi> and
<hi>water,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Elias</hi> both Preachers of all ſorts of men vnder the Law, were choſe to be with Chriſt in his
<hi>tranſmigration,</hi> that kings haue beene Preachers
<hi>Melehiſedech</hi> a King Prieſt, <hi>Dauid</hi> a King Prophet,
<hi>Salomon</hi> a King Preacher. But that which is aboue all, is that Chriſt Ieſus that came into <hi>the world</hi> to ſaue ſinners, that came to enrich it with his <hi>grace,</hi> to confirme it by his <hi>example,</hi> to redeeme it with his <hi>bloud,</hi> came to inſtruct it with his
<hi>doctrine,</hi> and to preach this <hi>Goſpell.</hi> For his ſake, wee therefore as <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes,</hi> and <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> beſeech you that yee receiue not the word of God <hi>this grace of God in vaine:</hi> By the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>mercie of God wee beſeech you,</hi> though yee deny the dignitie of <hi>preaching,</hi> yet acknowlege the <hi>power</hi> that hath called you to this ineſtimable light. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tells vs of
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> ſubiection of the people to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor; and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the authoritie of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14038:17"/>
               <hi>Paſtor</hi> ouer the people, I preſſe neither, but I call for the acknowledgment of the power <hi>of preaching: Paul</hi> warns frequently that they diſpiſe not <hi>Timothy,</hi> obey them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you, they are worthy of <hi>double honor that are ouer you</hi> haue them in <hi>ſingular loue,</hi> and eſteeme them <hi>highly</hi> that are oure you in the Lord, by <hi>authoritie</hi> this may bee <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted,</hi> but better by <hi>charitie</hi> to bee expected. <hi>Miſerable</hi> men!
<hi>wormes</hi> and no <hi>men,</hi> what are wee? <hi>clods</hi> of
<hi>earth,</hi> clothed with <hi>infirmitie,</hi> and <hi>mortalitie</hi> as ye are, <hi>peeces</hi> of <hi>clay</hi> hewen out of the <hi>ſame pit</hi> as yee are, wee are but <hi>fragments</hi> of men, tinkling <hi>cimballs,</hi> broken <hi>ceſternes,</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption equally <hi>acquainted</hi> with
<hi>vs</hi> as <hi>you:</hi> yet wee are the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> of Chriſt, his ſtrength is in our <hi>weakeneſſe,</hi> and he that hath ſaid <hi>diſpiſe not propheſie,</hi> hath enioyned not to
<hi>diſpiſe Timothy.</hi> Beloued, it yee <hi>deſire</hi> ſaluation, diſpiſe not <hi>Preachers,</hi> nor <hi>preaching,</hi> I neede not vrge this in this <hi>City,</hi> where the Lord hath as many <hi>acres</hi> of good Chriſtians, as in any ſuch quantitie of earth in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> yet if as in <hi>Iob,</hi> ſo in this <hi>aſſembly</hi> now the ſonnes of <hi>God</hi> are come to preſent themſelues before the <hi>Lord</hi> there be a <hi>Sathan</hi> here, ſo heere, any ſonne of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> that is a ſcorner of <hi>Preachers,</hi> into whoſe <hi>loathſome</hi> body <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> is ſtolne from <hi>hell,</hi> filling his
<hi>mouth</hi> with <hi>blaſphemie,</hi> againſt <hi>Gods miniſterie.</hi> Let him know that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> a kings hand was
<hi>withered,</hi> when hee onely would lay hold on a <hi>Prophet:</hi> that 2. Captaines,<note place="margin">1 King. 13.4.</note> 2. fifties fired from heauen when they onely would <hi>apprehend</hi> a <hi>Prophet:</hi> 42.
<hi>children</hi> torne in peeces,<note place="margin">2 King. 1.10.</note> by wilde beares, who only as children mocked a <hi>Prophet:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 2.24.</note> 250. deuoured by fire, <hi>Corah</hi> and all his complices, the men, houſes, goods, all deuoured by the earth,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.35.</note> who onely rebelled againſta
<hi>Prophet:</hi> Nay <hi>Miriam</hi> a holy women, ſtroken with a loathſome leproſie onely for a murmure againſt a <hi>Prophet.</hi> Neither King, nor <hi>Prieſt,</hi> neither <hi>Iudge,</hi> nor
<hi>Militarie</hi> man, neither <hi>Captaine,</hi> not <hi>Souldier,</hi> neither <hi>man,</hi> not <hi>woman,</hi> neither <hi>women,</hi> nor
<hi>children,</hi> haue eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14038:18"/>
               <hi>vengeance</hi> fot wronging
<hi>Prophets:</hi> and as if all Gods <hi>creatures</hi> were ready nor onely to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> them, but <hi>rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eue</hi> them, euen the moſt ſauage creatures. Crooping Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens fed <hi>Elias</hi> a <hi>Prophet,</hi> raging <hi>Lyons</hi> preſerued <hi>Damelia Prophet:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt.</note> 
               <hi>Aues paſcunt ferae parcunt, homines ſeuint,</hi> faith <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Beloued, I onely caſt this, dart, at the <hi>deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Atheiſt, who contemnes preaching, and is onely <hi>wittie</hi> in this kinde of <hi>wickedneſſe.</hi> Let it bee your <hi>care,</hi> yee <hi>watchfull</hi> Senators of this great
<hi>Citty</hi> to giue all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to this holy exerciſe, when it was
<hi>threatned</hi> by ſome <hi>popiſh Courtiers,</hi> in the ſiry raigne of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> that the Court ſhould be <hi>remooued</hi> from the
<hi>City,</hi> which would cauſe the <hi>Cities pouertie,</hi> it was nobly and <hi>reſolutely</hi> anſwered by the <hi>Lord-maior,</hi> they feared not, vnleſſe they could alſo remooue the <hi>currant</hi> of the Thames. Beloued, ſo long as the <hi>currant</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhall engirt your <hi>Citie,</hi> well are ye, and happy ſhall yee be. Giue all Chriſtian <hi>encouragement</hi> that the ſound of preaching may be heard in your ſtreetes; it were a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuite that in your
<hi>plantation</hi> of IRELAND that <hi>Land of</hi> IRE, where Gods wrath hath abounded for the want of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> yee endeauoured by thoſe
<hi>reuerend</hi> Byſhops that his ſacred Maieſtie placeth there toſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faithfull, painefull <hi>Preachers,</hi> in your new Citties: The
<hi>Londiner</hi> may <hi>plant,</hi> the <hi>Courtier</hi> may <hi>water,</hi> the <hi>Preacher</hi> onely by Gods aſſiſtance muſt <hi>bring ſoorth</hi> the encreaſe.<note place="margin">Plat.</note> There were ſometimes no <hi>Phyſitians</hi> in <hi>Athens,</hi> one wondered at it, and queſtioned it, but receiued this <hi>anſwere,</hi> becauſe no reward for Phiſitians: <hi>Yee haue Preachers as plentifully as any Citie</hi> of the world, you may <hi>bleſſe God for this: They haue in ſome places among you, as bountifull rewards as men of any vocation in the world, they may bloſſe God for this: Lawyers may watch ouer and deuour your ſtates; Phiſitians watch ouer and deſtroy your healths: Only preaching is able to ſaue your ſoules. All ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e neede of this: Many worthy conſecrate their ſonnes to this; ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14038:18"/>good ſoules I hope take comfort in this. Beloued, if there bee any conſolution in Chriſt Ieſus, if any comfort of loue, if any fellowſhippe of the Spirit, if any bowells and mercies open your hands, and at length bring foorth fruits of ſuch plentiſull prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</hi> Sit ye <hi>idle</hi> in the market, <hi>idle</hi> in the vineyard, <hi>idle</hi> in the Temple? The trumpe of <hi>an Archangell will terriſie you, the ſong of mercy ſhall be ſilenced, the voice of the Turtle ſhall ceaſe: Athens</hi> was <hi>Mater ſtudiorum, nouerca virtutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Shall London abound in preaching, and abound in ſinning, what is this, but to kill the Prophets, and build their Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres</hi> It was
<hi>Diues</hi> charitie, to ſend out from the dead, to preach to his brethren; But now it is our Sauiours mercy he is <hi>riſen</hi> from the
<hi>dead,</hi> and is come to preach the reſurrection, and the life, and you partake thoſe things, which the <hi>Angells</hi> deſire to looke into, and are neuer ſatisfied with looking therein, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>I beſeech you, Bleſſed</hi> and Beloued, by the care yee haue of your owne ſoules, by your hope of ſaluation, by all the mercies of God, by all the merits of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, by his agony and bloudy ſweate, by his
<hi>croſſe</hi> and <hi>paſſion,</hi> by his pretious death and
<hi>buriall,</hi> by his glorious <hi>reſurrection,</hi> &amp;
<hi>aſcenſion,</hi> let not your <hi>preaching</hi> of <hi>life,</hi> be the ſauour of death. Let at length <hi>preaching,</hi> purge your ſtreets of <hi>vnlawfull-gaine, clenſe</hi> your <hi>ſhoppes</hi> of <hi>deceit, melt</hi> your <hi>ſalſe ballances, quench</hi> your <hi>luſt, coole</hi> your <hi>luſts, abate</hi> your <hi>pride, aſſwage</hi> your <hi>malice, confound</hi> your couetous <hi>vicious deuiſes;</hi> that you may be reſtored to <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> and <hi>holineſſe,</hi> to the
<hi>Image</hi> of him that hath called you: I ſhould not end this
<hi>point</hi> till you beginne the <hi>practiſe,</hi> but the
<hi>ſtarre</hi> leades mee, I muſt follow further, for this Goſpell
<hi>goeth further,</hi> this <hi>Goſpell</hi> ſhall <hi>be preached through the whole world.</hi> My third part.</p>
            <p>There was light in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> when darkeneſſe in all
<hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3</note> that was ſtrange, but there was darkeneſſe in the <hi>Temple,</hi> when all the earth was full of
<hi>glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 6.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Glory</hi> in the earth, in the whole earth, the whole earth full of <hi>glory,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:14038:19"/>and the <hi>Temple</hi> full of
<hi>ſmoake,</hi> it is more ſtrange then that in <hi>Sodome,</hi> a iuſt man was found, when <hi>in Ieruſalem</hi> there was not one <hi>good man. Darkneſſe</hi> in the <hi>Temple,</hi> when light in all the
<hi>world?</hi> If the <hi>eye</hi> be darke how great is that
<hi>darkneſſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen. in Eſa. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Origen</hi> tells vs, this was a manifeſtation of the <hi>preaching</hi> of the Goſpell, to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and a blinding of the eyes of the
<hi>Iewes.</hi> But our Sauiour was ſent rather to the <hi>Iewes</hi> then
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> I am not ſent but to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of
<hi>Iſraell,</hi> go not into the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but to the loſt ſheepe of the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> here is that light as in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and darkneſſe ouer all the earth, and cruell
<hi>habitation?</hi> How ſhall this <hi>Goſpell</hi> bee preached throughout the world, when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> the greateſt part of the world were denied the <hi>Goſpell?</hi> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> anſwereth that the Lord would not partake the Goſpell to the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Hierom.</note> before it had beene offered the Iewes; It was
<hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſpeech, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.46. It was neceſſarie that the word of God, ſhould be firſt <hi>ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to you,</hi> but ſeeing yee put it from you, loe wee turne to the
<hi>Gentiles:</hi> Heere the <hi>Temple</hi> was full of <hi>ſmoake,</hi> and all the world full of glorie. The <hi>Iewes</hi> indeede had a light and whether this <hi>light</hi> were the ſeate of the <hi>Church,</hi> or ſcepter of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> proper it was to the Iewes. It was but <hi>lucerna</hi> a lampe, and at length extinguiſhed: But when the light was conueied to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> it was <hi>Lucifer</hi> the day ſtarre ſprung in their hearts,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſo diſtinguiſheth, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. the Law was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a law ſhining in a darke place, the Goſpell <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the day ſtarre in the dawning of the day, well might our Sauiour be called the light of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ ſt m</note> for he appeared by a ſtar to the <hi>Gentiles: Quare per ſtellam, quare magis per ſtellam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> as the mother of
<hi>Siſera</hi> anſwereth her ſelfe ſo doth he, the <hi>ſtar</hi> was as fit a ſigne for the <hi>Magi</hi> as the <hi>lambe</hi> for the
<hi>Shepheards,</hi> the <hi>lambe</hi> was <hi>borne, Shepheards</hi> are firſt told, of the <hi>lambe</hi> among the <hi>Iewes:</hi> the light of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14038:19"/>
               <hi>Iſraell</hi> appeared, men in the
<hi>ſtarres</hi> are directed by this ſtar, Chriſt Ieſus is the bright morning <hi>ſtar, Reu.</hi> 22.16. hee muſt be the light of the
<hi>Gentiles, Lucerna Moſes, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer Chriſtus, Iohannes vox, Chriſtus verlu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Moſes</hi> was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Church of the
<hi>Iewes</hi> the <hi>day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar</hi> muſt be the light of the <hi>Gentiles, Iohn Baptiſt</hi> the voice enough for the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the <hi>world. Ante reſurrectionem, ne abteritis poſt reſurrectionem, ite predicate,</hi> before the reſurrection, this <hi>commandement</hi> go not into the way of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> after, <hi>go teach all nations:</hi> This text is then the <hi>propheſie</hi> of the generall preaching of the Goſpell after the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Our Sauiour being driuen out of the
<hi>Temple,</hi> preſently healed a man blinde from his birth:<note place="margin">Theoph. Nazianz. Bede. Aquin.</note> the <hi>Greeke</hi> Fathers, and of the latine, <hi>Bede, Aquinas,</hi> and others, expound this of Chriſt being driuen from the Iewes, he healed the <hi>Gentiles</hi> blinde from their birth. Many <hi>col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections</hi> to this purpoſe the deſtroying
<hi>Angell</hi> in the <hi>peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> in <hi>Dauids</hi> time, ſheathed his ſword, not ouer the houſe of a Iewe, but ouer the houſe of
<hi>Araumah</hi> a Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, a Gentile: The Arke was brought home, not to
<hi>Dauids</hi> houſe, but to the houſe of <hi>Obed Edom,</hi> a
<hi>Gittite,</hi> a Gentile: Before, <hi>Abrahams</hi> buriall place, was purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of a ſtranger, a <hi>Gentile;</hi> the place to build the
<hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> bought of a <hi>ſtranger</hi> a <hi>Gentile,</hi> the field on which the <hi>Iewes</hi> beſtowed <hi>Iudas</hi> 30. peeces, was bought to bury ſtrangers <hi>Gentiles, Iob</hi> from <hi>Hus, Ruth</hi> from <hi>Moab, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> from <hi>Iericho, Salomons</hi> wife from <hi>Egipt,</hi> the famous Queene from <hi>Sheba,</hi> firſt fruites of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> the Wiſemen that came to Chriſt, the <hi>Centurion</hi> the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Souldier, <hi>Zacheus</hi> the great Vſurer, <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt Martyr, <hi>Cornelius</hi> the Captaine, <hi>Simon</hi> the Tanner, Queene of
<hi>Candaces</hi> Eunuch, were all Gentiles. I deny not but ſome parts of the Goſpell were knowne, to the heathen before they were <hi>preached,</hi> that Chriſt ſhould be borne, the <hi>Sibills foretold</hi> it, that hee ſhould bee the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14038:20"/>
               <hi>Redeemer, Tully de diuinatione:</hi> Of his miracle, <hi>Tacitus</hi> is not ſilent in his 5. booke: Of the Wiſe-mens ſtarre, <hi>Pliny</hi> in his 2. booke: Of the <hi>Innocents, Macrobius</hi> in his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnals:</hi> that Chriſt was the word, <hi>Plato</hi> in
<hi>Timaeo:</hi> that by this word all things were made, <hi>Amitius</hi> the
<hi>Platoniſt</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth: that Chriſt ſuffered,
<hi>Dioniſius</hi> the Atheiſt: But this was not <hi>enough,</hi> our Sauiour that would haue all men ſaued, and to come to the knowledge of the
<hi>truth,</hi> would <hi>haue all the ends of the world to heare of the ſaluation of our God.</hi> He ſent the Apoſtles to all nations:
<hi>Peter</hi> into <hi>Antiochia, Iohn</hi> into <hi>Aſia, Iames</hi> to
<hi>Syria, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> to <hi>Scithia, Phillip</hi> into <hi>Gallia, Thomas</hi> into <hi>Parthia, Bartholomew</hi> into <hi>Armenia, Mathew</hi> in
<hi>Ethiopia,</hi> and <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> into <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and vnto this Land, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, either Saint <hi>Paul</hi> as
<hi>Theodoret</hi> affirmes, or Saint <hi>Peter</hi> as <hi>Baronius,</hi> or
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> as moſt deliuer: So that it is not only as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſang, Praiſe the Lord ye houſe of
<hi>Leui,</hi> praiſe yee houſe of <hi>Aaron,</hi> praiſe the Lord yee houſe of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> but praiſe the Lord all yee <hi>Nations,</hi> praiſe him all yee <hi>Gentiles,</hi> all they that feare the Lord praiſe the Lord in all places of his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,</hi> praiſe the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal.
117.1.</note> for the ſound of the Goſpell <hi>is gone out</hi> into all the earth, and the preaching thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ends of the world, from
<hi>which light of the Gentiles,</hi> we gather this light of
<hi>Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> That all the world ſhall ſee the <hi>ſaluation</hi> of our God; the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> becauſe hee will haue all inexcuſable, ſend to al, come to all, preach to all, in all places of his <hi>Dominions: It was his Law in Deut.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10.</note> 10. <hi>that no Citty ſhould be deſtroyed before he offered Peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and though hee alwaies haue his iudgement ready, his bow bent, his arrowes prepared, his ſword ſheathed, his cuppe mingled, his weapons burniſhed,</hi> yet before his ſtorme of
<hi>iudgement,</hi> he ſends a ſhowre of <hi>mercy, warning</hi> before
<hi>woe:</hi> Euen <hi>Niniueh,</hi> and <hi>Tyrus,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> had warning; before hee will iudge the <hi>world</hi> with righteouſneſſe, he will ſhew them the light of his
<hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:14038:20"/>his way ſhall bee knowne vpon earth, his ſauing health among all <hi>nations:</hi> But is this fulfilled, <hi>it was Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids propheſie, their ſound is gone into all Lands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> Pſalm. 19.5. <hi>Eſayes proclamation, Hearken ô yee Iles, heare yee people that dwell from farre.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 49.1. Math. 28.20.</note> Eſay 49.1. <hi>Chriſts iniunction, Go teach all nations,</hi> Math. 28.20. <hi>Remiſſion of ſinnes ſhall be preached to all nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 24.47. Mark. 16.20.</note> Luk. 24.47 <hi>they preached eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where,</hi> Mark. 16.20
<hi>It is true, Quoad ad vitam crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, ad veniamre dimere voluit. I will poure my Spirit</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>vpon all fleſh,</hi> and againe,
<hi>all fleſh ſhall ſee the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God,</hi> and all the ends of the <hi>world</hi> haue ſeene the <hi>ſaluation</hi> of our God.
<hi>Chryſoſtome, Euthimius, Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact, Euſcbius, Anſelme</hi> affirme this generall publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon
<hi>Math,</hi> thinketh it was <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed before Ieruſalem</hi> was demoliſhed. But <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Ierome,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin.</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> and <hi>Bede,</hi> and the
<hi>Authour</hi> of the imperfect worke vpon <hi>Mathew,</hi> and moſt of the
<hi>Moderne,</hi> thinke that this Goſpell was not then, or is now ſo generally <hi>knowne,</hi> becauſe this is the laſt ſigne of the laſt dayes: <hi>Cyrill, Damaſcene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyrill Damaſcen. Theodoret. Auſtin in hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> expound thoſe places, <hi>non adhuc eſſe vniuerſalitatem praedicationis, ſed eſſe implenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hanc vaticinatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſucceſſione temporis: Auſtin</hi> to this purpoſe, <hi>verba Matthei non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc completa, ſed eſſe complenda, Aquinas,</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Vera ſunt Mathei verba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel.</note> 
               <hi>non reſpectu generalis praedicationis, ſed propter certitudinem diuinae praeordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi> It is Saint
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſeruation, that the <hi>Elders</hi> ſpake to the
<hi>Lambe, Redimiſti nos, ex omni tribu, lingua, populo, natione, non dixit omnem tribum, omnem populum, omnemlinguam,</hi> herein <hi>incomplete generis diſtributio,</hi> as in this <hi>go teach all nations,</hi> that is ſome of all. But this <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere</hi> is not full: The beſt <hi>anſwere</hi> of the former <hi>Authors</hi> is <hi>Thomas, vtitur praeterito pro futuro,</hi> or this <hi>Euangeliſ fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma in omnibus gentibus praedicatur, at Eccleſia in omnibus Gentibus non adhuc aedificatur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſt. ad Heſich.</note> And <hi>Zanchius</hi> concludeth all, <hi>Certum eſt Euangelium ad omnes gentes pertinere, non
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14038:21"/>adhuc ad omnes pernenire;</hi> for in the time of Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> there were as he witneſſeth ſome Nations
<hi>quos nec acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perant, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> andiuerant.</hi> For the Goſpell in the primitiue Church was <hi>Orbis ludibrium, &amp; opprobrium.</hi> And long after in the time of <hi>Prudentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prudent.</note> 
               <hi>Nunc dogmanobis Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum naſcitur poſt euocatos demum inde conſules.</hi> It was a Propheſie, euery age fulfilleth a <hi>peece</hi> of it, the neerer the <hi>world</hi> to the <hi>conſummation,</hi> the more generall ſhould be the Goſpells <hi>publication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Minut. Fel.</note> 
               <hi>Ingratinos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Min: Faelix,</hi> we are vnthankfull, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> groweth more ripe in our time,<note place="margin">Copern.</note> ſome think the <hi>ſun</hi> euery yeer deſcendeth ſo much neerer the earth, certainely the
<hi>Goſpell</hi> in euery age, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth more plentifully in the world. The Goſpell ſhall be preached through the <hi>world,</hi> bleſſed are they that haue <hi>a hand</hi> to helpe ſuch a worke. That it is by
<hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> ſaid to haue beene <hi>preached</hi> to all nations, that ſpeech is to be referred, either to <hi>Prophecie,</hi> or to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> or <hi>Hyperbole.</hi> Certaine it is, that yet it is not ſo <hi>preached,</hi> &amp; as <hi>certain</hi> that this Goſpel ſhall be preached. <hi>Lyra</hi> vpon the words of Chriſt go teach all <hi>nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra.</note> 
               <hi>Hic diuulgatio Dominicae reſurrectionis,</hi> behold by this Commiſlion a
<hi>diuulgation</hi> of Chriſts <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> and of all the parts of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> that euer haue beene publiſhed, none more generally then this. The <hi>Scribes</hi> asked a ſigne, Chriſt giues them no ſigne, but of the Prophet <hi>Ionas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math.
12.39.</note> the <hi>Phariſes</hi> they asked a ſigne, Chriſt anſwers, no ſigne, but the ſigne of the Prophet <hi>Ionas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 8.11.</note> At the ſame time <hi>Saduces</hi> came, and haue the ſame <hi>anſwere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16.4.</note> no ſigne, but of the Prophet <hi>Ionas: Iewes, Scribes, Phariſes, Saduces,</hi> no ſigne, but of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Aboue all other
<hi>duties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.8.</note> he required his Apoſtles ſhould in <hi>Hieruſalem, Iudea, Samaria,</hi> and vnto the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt parts of the earth bee witneſſes to him: of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther points, witneſſes of his reſurrection. Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">Act. 1.22. Act. 2.32.</note> in his firſt Sermon in
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> witneſſeth that God hath raiſed vp <hi>Ieſus: Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> preach this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14038:21"/>to the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> The reſurrection of
<hi>Ieſus, Acts</hi> 4.2. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> teſtifie this to the deuout <hi>Greekes,</hi> Chriſt that hath ſuffered is riſen,
<hi>Acts</hi> 17.3. And of all other Apoſtles, <hi>Paul</hi> as if he had beene the Apoſtle of the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> is moſt plentifull. No
<hi>Prophet,</hi> no <hi>Apoctle</hi> euer more abundant in any point, then he in the <hi>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> To the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chriſt roſe againe for our <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Rom.</hi> 4.25. To the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Chriſt died and roſe againe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. To the
<hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> Chriſt died and roſe againe, 1
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.14. To the <hi>Philippians,</hi> The power of Chriſts
<hi>reſurrection, Phil.</hi> 3.10. To <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> The reſurrection of Chriſt who aboliſhed death, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. In a word, he preached no other <hi>Doctrine</hi> to the <hi>Grecians</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> to the <hi>Stoicks</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> to the <hi>Scribes</hi> and
<hi>Phariſes</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to <hi>Feſtus</hi> and
<hi>Agrippa</hi> at <hi>Caeſarea:</hi> In euery <hi>Court</hi> where he was queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, he crieth out, <hi>I ſtand for the reſurrection of the dead,</hi> as if ready to preach through the world that this <hi>Goſpell</hi> is to be preached to all Nations.</p>
            <p>The vſe of which point,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> of the generall preaching of the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt through the world, ſhould ſtirre vs vp to a thankfull acknowledgement of the plentifull enioying of this mercy. It is <hi>the manifold grace of God,</hi> 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10. <hi>The exceeding grace of God, Rom.</hi> 5.15.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.10. Rom. 5.15. 1 Tim 1.14. Pſal. 130.7.</note> 
               <hi>The ſuperabundant grace of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.14. <hi>The plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Redemption of the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 130.7. That wee that <hi>ſate in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death,</hi> haue ſeene this great light: that wee haue euen from the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>faith</hi> receiued this <hi>faith.</hi> I know our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> doe claime the honour of <hi>conuerting</hi> our <hi>Nation:</hi> Were it ſo, we might complaine that the <hi>Euill man</hi> hath ſowne <hi>Tares.</hi> But as the
<hi>field</hi> was ſowne with <hi>ſeed</hi> by the <hi>huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman</hi> before the <hi>Aduerſarie</hi> ſowed <hi>Tares,</hi> ſo wee had
<hi>Religion</hi> before they knew <hi>Superſtition.</hi> They attribute much to <hi>Auſtine</hi> their <hi>Monke,</hi> who was as farre from the ſteps as time of bleſſed <hi>S. Auſtine.</hi> For which <hi>Monk,</hi> it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14038:22"/>is vpon record, that neither his <hi>pride</hi> could ſtoope to ſuch a <hi>labour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gildes. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de.
<hi>Gen. 22.14.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nger in Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>one and twenty hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Monkes, 1. Archbiſhop, and 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ops in tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e parts of</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Saxon
<hi>Chron of</hi> Peterborough Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in <hi>the blacke bloudy proud an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng Monke in his ſpleene to</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew infinite bloud, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtroyed more</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>then euer Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie ſaued</hi> ſoules.</note> nor his
<hi>learning</hi> deſerued any ſuch <hi>honour. Gildas</hi> and
<hi>Bede,</hi> and our owne Chronicles tell vs, that the ancient and noble
<hi>Britaines</hi> firſt receiued the faith among vs, as if <hi>Dominus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> monte,</hi> the Lord would bee worſhipped firſt in the mountaine. Then
<hi>Britaine</hi> was the <hi>fleece</hi> with the <hi>deaw,</hi> and all the ſurrounding Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries as <hi>Gedeons</hi> fleece <hi>drie;</hi> though now this, as <hi>Gedeons</hi> fleece full of <hi>deaw,</hi> and the mountainous parts as <hi>Gede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> floore now <hi>drie,</hi> by the
<hi>deſolation</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> there, and by the
<hi>negligence,</hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> or <hi>indulgence,</hi> or all, of thoſe that ſhould ouerſee it. But for that <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke Auſtine</hi> the <hi>Monke,</hi> hee <hi>ſupplanted Religion</hi> there, neuer <hi>planted</hi> it here. <hi>Beda</hi> mentioneth his
<hi>prodigious</hi> inſufferable pride, which made the reuerend <hi>Britiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> refuſe him. If he were our <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or
<hi>Euangeliſt,</hi> as <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iouinian, Si Apoſtolus,</hi> If he were our <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,</hi> where did he preach? If our <hi>Euangeliſt,</hi> what did he write? As <hi>Varus</hi> ſpake of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius,</hi> He entred the Land <hi>poore,</hi> and left our Church
<hi>poore;</hi> hee cauſed the death of many <hi>bodies,</hi> and it is doubt he neuer gained <hi>ſoules.</hi> It hath beene our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> generall claime, as that madde man in <hi>Athenaeus,</hi> who claimed all the ſhips came into the <hi>harbour;</hi> or as the <hi>Deuill</hi> on the
<hi>Pinnacle,</hi> All the Kingdomes of the earth: ſo they claime to bee the only <hi>conuerters</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> and they the generall
<hi>Preachers</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> Whereas they neuer yet
<hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched</hi> whereſoeuer they came but vpon one eſpeciall Text; and in all parts of the world where they haue beene, they haue preached that ſo
<hi>powerfully,</hi> that their <hi>hearers</hi> haue <hi>wept,</hi> and
<hi>bled,</hi> and <hi>died</hi> for learning that Doctrine. Their Text is,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 10.34. <hi>I came not to ſend peace, but a ſword.</hi> Looke but vpon the eſtate of <hi>India,</hi> which as <hi>Veſputius</hi> teſtifieth was conuerted by <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> where yee may finde more curſed <hi>Prodigies</hi> then euer the <hi>Sunne</hi> beheld in any
<hi>Mappe of miſerie:</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14038:22"/>where the <hi>Romiſh Apoſtles</hi> did exceed <hi>Cain,</hi> or if poſſibly <hi>Iudas;</hi> where they
<hi>rauiſhed,</hi> and then <hi>murthered Queens,</hi> tore <hi>infants</hi> in <hi>peeces,</hi> caſt men to <hi>maſtiues,</hi> cut children in
<hi>collops</hi> to feed <hi>dogges:</hi> Happy was his inuention moſt
<hi>bloudy. Men</hi> neuer did the like, <hi>Deuils</hi> could doe no more,<note place="margin">Veſſuſ.</note> 
               <hi>Religion</hi> was there (as
<hi>Veſputius</hi> iuſtifieth) long before the Gold-hungry, bloud-thirſty
<hi>Portugall</hi> or <hi>Pope,</hi> was heard of; Churches erected, Biſhops eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, whole Countries baptized. <hi>Oroſius</hi> and
<hi>Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius,</hi> and <hi>Iunius,</hi> and <hi>Baronius,</hi> tell vs, that
<hi>S. Thomas</hi> who conuerted the Countrey, lieth buried there, and that from his time they haue had <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> and
<hi>maried Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> among them. The
<hi>Romans</hi> deſcended from <hi>Edom,</hi> ſay the <hi>Iewes, Edom</hi> had a name of <hi>bloud,</hi> Mount <hi>Seyr</hi> was their
<hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Hill of bloud,</hi> and <hi>Acheldama</hi> their <hi>purchaſe,</hi> the <hi>Field of bloud:</hi> The name of
<hi>bloud,</hi> and poſſeſſion of <hi>bloud,</hi> is in the
<hi>Romiſh Religion.</hi> Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> when once they grow
<hi>Romiſh,</hi> againſt the <hi>Nature</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> become
<hi>bloudie,</hi> which I impute to the<note n="*" place="margin">The Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards &amp; ſome parts of the Engliſh Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Rome</hi> are ſeated in bloudy <hi>Neroes</hi> ruines.</note> 
               <hi>ſituation</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Colledge</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> which is founded on the ruines of
<hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> houſe. But of all the ſtories of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or
<hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> of all the <hi>Tragedies</hi> plotted in <hi>hell,</hi> acted vnder <hi>heauen,</hi> neuer any ſo <hi>horrid,</hi> as the <hi>bloudy Baptiſme</hi> of <hi>India</hi> by the vmbragious <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> They haue long inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſecond part of that <hi>Tragedie</hi> to be acted here. God grant their <hi>rods</hi> and <hi>ſcourges</hi> prouided in 88. be not growing <hi>Serpents</hi> and <hi>Scorpions</hi> to bring on Gods bitter
<hi>ſeueritie</hi> to plague our baſe <hi>ſecuritie.</hi> The
<hi>Goſpell</hi> is not further gone into all the world, then their
<hi>crueltie</hi> is knowne. <hi>Nulla poſterit as taceat, ſed nulla probet.</hi> Beloued,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> wee enioy the
<hi>Goſpell</hi> in a more gracious manner then any part of the world: wee enioyed it with the <hi>ſoonest,</hi> yea and before many parts of the world. When <hi>Brith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald</hi> the <hi>Monke,</hi> before the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> was carefull about ſucceſſion of the <hi>Crowne,</hi> hee had a
<hi>viſion,</hi> and heard a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14038:23"/>
               <hi>voice,</hi> That the Kingdome of
<hi>England</hi> was Gods owne Kingdome, and for it God himſelfe would prouide. <hi>Boniface</hi> writing to <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, giues teſtimonie, <hi>Anglicanam Nationem non eſſe ſubalternam,</hi> that this was one of the principall Nations of <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi> And in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> challenging the chiefe place in a <hi>Prouinciall</hi> aboue the <hi>Engliſh, Iulius</hi> the ſecond ſentenced it for <hi>England</hi> before <hi>Spaine.</hi> I ſpeake not this as if the <hi>Popes</hi> fauour could doe vs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For both that
<hi>Teſtimonie,</hi> and the Title <hi>Defenſor Fidei,</hi> we are no more beholden to the <hi>Pope,</hi> then to his elder brother <hi>Caiaphas</hi> the
<hi>High Prieſt</hi> for his <hi>Expedit.</hi> God hath not dealt ſo with other <hi>Nations:</hi> we can fetch our <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> from better
<hi>Authors.</hi> About the 400. yeere,<note place="margin">Chryſoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>homil. quod Chriſtus Deus. Hilar. de Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis. Athanaſ. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ſecund.</note>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Inſulae Britannicae in ipſo Oceano poſitae, ſenſerunt virtutem Dei.</hi> Before this, in the 360.
<hi>Hilary</hi> writes, <hi>Prouinciarum Britanicarum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</hi> Yet before this, in the 300. <hi>Athanaſius, Epiſcopi Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniarum ſeſe ad Concilium contulerunt,</hi> ſpeaking of the Councell of <hi>Sardis.</hi> Yet a Century before this, in the 200. yeere <hi>Tertuſſian</hi> witneſſed,
<hi>Britannorum inacceſſa Romanis loca ſubduntur Chriſto.</hi> Yet in the very firſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, in the very beginning of that Century,
<hi>Nicephorus</hi> records it,<note place="margin">Nicephorus.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Zelotes doctrinam Euangely ad Inſulas Britannicas profert.</hi> More then all this, who could ſooner haue this doctrine of the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> then we? Who could teach it ſurer then <hi>Ioſeph of Arimathea,</hi> whom the moſt affirme to <hi>preach,</hi> and <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>die</hi> with vs? God hath not done ſo with all <hi>Nations.</hi> Shall it be ſaid of vs, that is obſerued of the firſt borne in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Priores peiores,</hi> the firſt <hi>borne,</hi> worſt <hi>bred?</hi> Had wee the
<hi>Goſpell</hi> ſooner then others, and haue brought forth leſſe
<hi>fruit</hi> then others? In <hi>Iurie</hi> was God knowne, his name was great in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> At <hi>Salem</hi> in his Tabernacle, and his dwelling in <hi>Zion.</hi> But the <hi>holy Citie</hi> became a
<hi>harlot,</hi> a <hi>cage,</hi> a <hi>cane,</hi> a <hi>denne,</hi> a
<hi>dungeon of deſolation,</hi> becauſe ſhe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14038:23"/>embraced not thoſe things belonging to her
<hi>peace.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, our <hi>Sauiours</hi> words be thunderbolts,
<hi>Luk.</hi> 13.3. twice repeated,<note place="margin">Luk 13.3.</note>
               <hi>Except yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh:</hi> Let them not be as <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> as lightnings fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on beaſts, not comming to obſeruation.<note place="margin">Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> When <hi>Xauerius</hi> came to preach to them of <hi>laponia,</hi> and the people were ſtrangely affected, accuſing God to be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>mercifull</hi> nor <hi>iuſt,</hi> if none could bee ſaued without this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> expoſtulating why had ſo many regions not knowne it, how miſerable their <hi>parents, friends, neighbours</hi> were, who were dead without this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the poore <hi>Indians</hi> with wounded <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>ſtreaming eyes,</hi> were anſwered, that the more carefully they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this
<hi>light,</hi> becauſe it was denied to others, though offered to them. God was the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> though a <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite</hi> the <hi>Author.</hi> Beloued, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> that bee preached through the whole world, but God hath not dealt ſo with all <hi>Nations</hi> as with vs. Our Land is
<hi>Paradiſe,</hi> here is the tree of <hi>knowledge:</hi> that tree of alltrees was <hi>Adams</hi> curſe. If our knowledge <hi>ſwell,</hi> and our conſcience <hi>pine,</hi> if wee <hi>conceiue</hi> in the <hi>eare,</hi> and be <hi>barren</hi> in the <hi>heart,</hi> if wee grow <hi>raſh</hi> in
<hi>cenſuring, peremptorie</hi> in <hi>talking, faſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> in
<hi>hearing, hard-hearted</hi> in <hi>obeying, hypocriticall</hi> in
<hi>profeſſing,</hi> let vs not deceiue our ſelues, our <hi>faith</hi> is a vaine <hi>preſuming,</hi> our <hi>holineſſe hypocriſie,</hi> our
<hi>zeale furie.</hi> and better were it not to haue knowne the way of
<hi>truth.</hi> But I hope <hi>better things</hi> of you all, and therefore I caſt <hi>Anko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for my firſt part, and make more haſte with that that followeth. The time is pretious, and my ointment is very pretious.
<hi>Whereſoeuer this Goſpell, &amp;c.</hi> I now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne with the vniuerſall <hi>promulgation</hi> of this ointment. <hi>This that this woman hath done, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt of the Act, This.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This.</hi>] And what was this?<note place="margin">2. Part.</note> They that take <hi>this woman</hi> to be <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> obſerue that ſhe neuer came to Chriſt, but fell at his feet. In the houſe of the <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14038:24"/>Luk.</hi> 7.38. When ſhe beſought him for
<hi>Lazarus, Iohn</hi> 11.31 When ſhe heard him preach, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.34. After his reſurrection, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28 9 When ſhe anointed him,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 12.3. A thing moſt commendable. But this is not the
<hi>This</hi> that is ſo <hi>commended.</hi> There is one <hi>ſtrange cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance</hi> in this <hi>act</hi> of her <hi>anointing,</hi> neue done to any but our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and neuer to our <hi>Sauiour</hi> but by this
<hi>woman,</hi> She wiped his <hi>feet</hi> with the <hi>haire</hi> of her
<hi>head,</hi> the greateſt <hi>humilitie</hi> that might be: The more
<hi>humble,</hi> the more <hi>happy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierome</note>
               <hi>Nunquid decrat iſti mulier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſudarium, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teolum aliquod,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Hierome:</hi> Was her <hi>cintment</hi> ſo pretious, and ſhe ſo poore, that ſhee could not bring a <hi>Napkin,</hi> or <hi>cloth,</hi> or <hi>handkerchiefe? Nihil dignius capillis, nihil proprium magis:</hi> What more dainty? What more worthy? Shee wiped her <hi>Sauiours</hi> feet with the haire of her head. If it were our <hi>Sauiours</hi> promiſe to the iuſt,
<hi>The haires of your head are numbred,</hi> and, <hi>Not ſo much as a haire of your head ſhall periſh;</hi> then happy of all the <hi>Iust</hi> was
<hi>Mary,</hi> happy the <hi>haires of her head,</hi> which wiping her teares from the feet of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> wiped away the faults of her owne
<hi>ſoule.</hi> This was honourable, but this is not the <hi>This</hi> that is ſo commended. The <hi>ointment</hi> was choice, and her choice of the ointment is <hi>commended.</hi> It was <hi>Spikenard. India</hi> is not honoured for <hi>Gold, Babylon</hi> for <hi>Corne, Tyrus</hi> for <hi>Purple, Libanus</hi> for <hi>Cedars, Arabia</hi> for <hi>Spices, Perſia</hi> for
<hi>Oiles,</hi> more then this <hi>oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> aboue all <hi>ointments</hi> is honoured. Euery <hi>Euangelist</hi> hath a ſeuerall attribute to honour this ointment: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mark.</hi> 14 3. very ſumptuous
<hi>ointment,</hi> ſo <hi>Plutarch</hi> vſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>S. Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, very honourable oile,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 12.3. ſo <hi>Athenaeus</hi> vſeth the word
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; our <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ointment of greater honour, and dearer price, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.7. ſo <hi>Suidas</hi> vſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Nay <hi>Iudas</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the
<hi>ointment</hi> praiſe enough, though he condemne the <hi>act,</hi> though he murmur out, <hi>To what purpoſe is this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14038:24"/>waſte?</hi> which was a ſtrange queſtion, that the ſonne of <hi>perdition</hi> ſhould aske <hi>Quorſum perditio haec?</hi> when neuer any thing was loſt by our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> but this
<hi>ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> whoſe damned <hi>murthering murmur</hi> this was, <hi>Quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum perditio? Peraitio tua exte Iuda, Iudas,</hi> thou ſonne of <hi>perdition,</hi> thou art thy owne <hi>perdition.</hi> But <hi>Iudas</hi> (I ſay) did praiſe this <hi>ointment,</hi> nay praiſe it more then any other, eſteemed it farre more worth then hee eſteemed his
<hi>Maſter,</hi> for he ſold his <hi>Maſter</hi> for 30. <hi>peeces,</hi> in the 15. verſe of this chapter, and val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed this ointment at 300. <hi>pence, Iohn</hi> 12.5. The ointment was <hi>Spik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nard, pretious,</hi> very
<hi>pretious,</hi> yet it is not the <hi>ointment</hi> that is ſo praiſed. This is not the <hi>This:</hi> What then was this <hi>This?</hi> Sure though not the <hi>ointment,</hi> yet the <hi>anointing</hi> might be ſo
<hi>commended.</hi> It was indeed much that ſhee <hi>bought,</hi> and
<hi>brought,</hi> and <hi>vſed</hi> the <hi>ointment,</hi> imployed her ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and her <hi>earneſt labour,</hi> in the <hi>anointing</hi> of Chriſt. We neuer reade that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> had any <hi>gifts</hi> giuen him, but <hi>Gold,</hi> and <hi>Spices,</hi> and <hi>Ointments:</hi> The Wiſe men offered <hi>Gold,</hi> as to a <hi>King;</hi> and <hi>Spices</hi> for
<hi>Incenſe,</hi> as to a <hi>God;</hi> and this woman <hi>ointments</hi> twice, as to a <hi>Man: Royaltie</hi> is noted in the <hi>Gold, Diuinitie</hi> by the <hi>Incenſe, Mortalitie</hi> by the <hi>Ointment.</hi> So Chriſt applieth it in the 12. verſe, <hi>In that ſhe powred this ointment on my body, ſhee did it for my buriall.</hi> Neuer was he otherwiſe anointed: He was anointed (ſaith <hi>Damaſcene</hi>) ſpiritually.<note place="margin">Damaſe.</note> 
               <hi>Corpus diuinit ate ſua vngens vt Deus, vnctus vt homo, quandoqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; hoc &amp; illud eſt.</hi> Otherwiſe corporally he was not anointed, he needed not, hee vſed no other ointment, yet fit it was this woman ſhould ſo anoint him, though not fit to anoint him as <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt was anointed, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 3. or
<hi>Dauid</hi> the King, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. or <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet,
1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. for wee haue receiued anointing from him, ſaith <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27. yet I ſay fit it was, for it was a Prophecie, that Chriſt ſhould be ſo anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23 5. anointed ſo at the <hi>Table,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.5.</note> Thou prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14038:25"/>a <hi>Table</hi> before mee, ſaith the
<hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> thou anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt my head with <hi>oile.</hi> This is
<hi>ſomewhat,</hi> yet this is not the <hi>This</hi> that is ſo commended:
<hi>ſomewhat</hi> it is, yet, what it is wee know not. It was our
<hi>Sauiours</hi> ſpeech, When thou <hi>faſteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Lyra.</hi>
               </note> anoint thy <hi>head, Matth.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Palestinis mos erat in Feſtis caput vngendi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyra;</hi> In <hi>Paleſtine</hi> they vſed in their
<hi>Feaſts</hi> to anoint their <hi>heads.</hi> But our <hi>Sauiour</hi> altereth that cuſtome, When thou <hi>faſteſt,</hi> anoint thy
<hi>head.</hi> In this act the command of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and the cuſtome of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> though contrary one to the other, are fulfilled. Chriſt at the feaſt is <hi>anointed,</hi> this was the
<hi>cuſtome</hi> of the <hi>Countrey; Mary</hi> faſteth and
<hi>anointeth</hi> her <hi>head,</hi> her <hi>head</hi> was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> here is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> this is the <hi>This,</hi> She anointed her <hi>head Chriſt, in the 7. verſe ſhe anointed the
<hi>head</hi> of her <hi>head Chriſt.</hi> Not the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ile,</hi> though
<hi>pretious;</hi> nor the <hi>endeuour,</hi> though <hi>laborious;</hi> nor the <hi>action,</hi> though <hi>religious;</hi> but the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner of the
<hi>action</hi> made the <hi>ointment</hi> odoriferous. God (ſay the
<hi>Canoniſts</hi>) loueth <hi>Aduerbes</hi> better then <hi>Adiectiues: Non quàm bonum, ſed quàm bene;</hi> Not the <hi>matter,</hi> but the <hi>manner</hi> receiues the <hi>commendation.</hi> It is <hi>Origens</hi> note,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.37.</note> that the <hi>ointment</hi> of the ſinfull woman in <hi>Luke</hi> hath no <hi>commendation:</hi> A woman that was a <hi>ſinner</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> brought an <hi>Alablaſter box</hi> of ointment, ſhee brought <hi>ointment,</hi> but <hi>Mary</hi> very pretious <hi>ointment;</hi> ſhe anointed his <hi>feet,</hi> but <hi>Mary</hi> anointeth his <hi>head: Mary</hi> hath choſen the better part.<note place="margin">Chriſolog.</note> 
                  <hi>At quaenam haec huius capitis vnctio?</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſologus:</hi> What meant this anointing of his <hi>head?</hi> For it may ſeeme <hi>raſh,</hi> and <hi>rude,</hi> that a <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> how good ſoeuer, ſhould ſuddenly when our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ur</hi> ſate at
<hi>meat,</hi> powre <hi>ointment,</hi> how pretious ſoeuer, vpon his
<hi>head,</hi> and <hi>face:</hi> Either there is ſome <hi>myſterie</hi> in it, or it had neuer beene ſo commended. Some tell vs that herein was
<hi>Agnitio Diuinitatis,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers <hi>Contemplatio Reſurrectionis,</hi> to which the Text giueth <hi>warrant,</hi> others <hi>Confeſſio Maieſtatis &amp; Gloriae Chriſti. Origen</hi> on this place,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14038:25"/>
                  <hi>Opus bonum quod fecimus propter Deum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Origen.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſecundum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; ad gloriam Dei, eſt vnguentum ſuper caput Chriſti effuſum.</hi> And
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> applieth it ſo;<note place="margin">Chryſ ſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Caput Christi vngas, ſi omnia in Chriſti gloriam referas. S. Bernard</hi> the ſame words; <hi>Gloria quae ex bonis actionibus proficiſcitur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>ad Deum referenda. Contrition</hi> by <hi>repentance</hi> doth waſh Chriſts <hi>feet, Deuotion</hi> by <hi>faith</hi> anointeth his <hi>head, Almes</hi> doe anoint his <hi>feet, Praier</hi> powres the ointment on his <hi>head, Workes of mercy</hi> may waſh his <hi>feet,</hi> but yeelding him due <hi>glory</hi> doth anoint his <hi>head:</hi> This is the <hi>This</hi> receiueth this
<hi>reward,</hi> Shee gaue <hi>glory</hi> to God by this <hi>action;</hi> by this <hi>vnction,</hi> her light did ſhine before <hi>men,</hi> and ſhe did
<hi>glorifie</hi> her Father which is in heauen. And now her ſweet ſauouring <hi>ointment</hi> yeelds vs this aſſured ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Doctrine:
<hi>Good workes be not accepted by God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
                  <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſuch as are directed to the glory of God.</hi> The reaſon, Where the end is <hi>wanting,</hi> the action is <hi>halting,</hi> and God will receiue no <hi>lame</hi> or <hi>blinde</hi> ſacrifice. If I ſeeke to pleaſe men, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſhould not bee the ſeruant of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1 10. If wee receiue the witneſſe of <hi>men,</hi> if wee ſeeke <hi>glory,</hi> by any good worke among <hi>men,</hi> wee anoint our ſelues, not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not his <hi>head,</hi> not his
<hi>feet,</hi> but our <hi>ſelues.</hi> In ſuch a caſe, <hi>Fumus flammam ſuffocat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> the
<hi>ſmoake</hi> choaketh the <hi>fire,</hi> and the froth of
<hi>oſtentation</hi> riſeth no ſooner, but falleth to the <hi>depth:</hi> There is the <hi>worme</hi> in the <hi>gourd, ruſt</hi> in the <hi>gold,</hi> a <hi>fire</hi> commeth out of the <hi>bramble</hi> to deuoure the <hi>Cedar. Tully</hi> cals <hi>Demoſthenes, Teniculum Demoſthenem,</hi> becauſe it pleaſed him going in the ſtreet to heare euen women and water-bearers whiſper, <hi>Hic eſt ille Demoſthenes.</hi> A wiſe man will not, a good man cannot entertaine thoughts of <hi>vaine-glory,</hi> which doe ſtrangle all worthy holy actions. In ſuch a caſe, the worke (though neuer ſo ſeemingly <hi>good</hi>) is but a fooles wonder, and the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> but a wiſe mans foole. <hi>Vaine-glory</hi> cannot ſwell ſo <hi>high,</hi> but <hi>vengeance</hi> will ſit <hi>aboue</hi> it; nor lift vp it ſelfe ſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14038:26"/>lofty</hi> but God will euer <hi>ouer-looke it.</hi> Our Sauiour nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>deſired,</hi> nor <hi>accepted</hi> the glory of the <hi>world,</hi> looking with no other eye thereon, then
<hi>Phiſitians</hi> on the <hi>diſeaſes</hi> of their <hi>Patients,</hi> his <hi>profeſſion</hi> was I ſeeke not my owne <hi>glory,</hi> Ioh.
8.50. They that thinke, that they poſſeſſe <hi>all things haue nothing,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.10. They that are proud of <hi>knowledge</hi> know nothing, 1 Tim. 6.3. He that thinketh himſelfe to be <hi>ſomething,</hi> is nothing, Gal. 6.3. S. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>nothing</hi> beyond the chiefe Apoſtles, confeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>nothing,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. Our bleſſed Sauiour conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this <hi>point,</hi> if I honour my ſelfe my honour is <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing,</hi> Ioh. 8.54. and therefore our aime of our actions, ſhould be as <hi>this of Mary,</hi> to the honour of our
<hi>Maſter,</hi> that all things may bee done to the glory of God the
<hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vſe whereof,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> as it ſhould euer bee <hi>welcome,</hi> ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially moſt
<hi>holeſome</hi> now to purge all <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of
<hi>hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>vaine-glory,</hi> in the bleſſed
<hi>occaſion</hi> of our <hi>meeting</hi> which is as the <hi>anncinting</hi> of Chriſt, and I doubt not <hi>entended</hi> to the glory of our <hi>gratious God,</hi> yet ſeeing <hi>Sathan</hi> is euer buſieſt in the beſt
<hi>actions,</hi> let euery man ſtand in <hi>feare,</hi> that hee deceiue not his owne <hi>ſoule:</hi> The temptations of <hi>vaine-glory</hi> of all other are moſt full of <hi>danger,</hi> moſt full of <hi>doubt,</hi> hardeſt to be <hi>knowne,</hi> not as the <hi>inſinuations</hi> of other vices,
<hi>open</hi> and <hi>plaine,</hi> but <hi>priuy</hi> and <hi>craftie,</hi> creeping vpon a man, with a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> low complement, <hi>binding</hi> the eyes with a <hi>cobwebbe</hi> vaile of <hi>vanitie,</hi> and then with a
<hi>falſe</hi> key of <hi>ſelfe-loue</hi> opening the heart to draw in that Spirit which turneth <hi>Angells</hi> into <hi>Deuills.</hi> Beloued, your
<hi>alabaſter</hi> box is <hi>faire,</hi> ſee your <hi>ointment</hi> be
<hi>ſweete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierem.</note> 
               <hi>In hoc genere Marmoris vnguenta ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantur illibata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome;</hi> farre be it that in an <hi>alabaſter</hi> box there ſhould be poiſon, or in the
<hi>cenſor</hi> of your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe,</hi> an vnſauory perſume, yee haue annointed the <hi>feet</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and I hope great is your
<hi>reward</hi> in heauen; yet the ſinner did ſo much, <hi>Faemina peccatrix in ciuirate,</hi> ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14038:26"/>I ſay? the ſinfull Citie hath done no more, then that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous</hi> ſinner in the <hi>Citie,</hi> I will not, I muſt not, I <hi>hope</hi> I may ſay the <hi>holy</hi> Citie, the Cittie of
<hi>God</hi> hath annointed the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>feete</hi> of her Sauiour to the glory of <hi>God,</hi> this worke that yee haue done <hi>is</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good worke, theſe little ones are the Lords
<hi>feet,</hi> let not the <hi>beſt</hi> heere, deſpiſe one of theſe
<hi>little ones,</hi> for I ſay vnto you, <hi>that in heauen the Angells doe alwaies behold the face of the Father which is in heauen:</hi> Let other places bee honoured for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>bleſſings</hi> in them, <hi>Venice</hi> for
<hi>riches, Bononia</hi> for <hi>fruits, Naples</hi> for <hi>nobilitie, Millane</hi> for <hi>beauty, Rauenna</hi> for <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quity, Florence</hi> for
<hi>pollicie,</hi> but of all Chriſtian <hi>Cities,</hi> This of yours, for this <hi>Nurſerie</hi> of your <hi>Inſants</hi> and <hi>Orphans</hi> hath
<hi>excelied.</hi> I denie not but beſides this, many other <hi>Porches</hi> of <hi>Betheſdas</hi> poole, are bleſſed by you, when I come to the
<hi>memoriall</hi> which is as the <hi>Mart,</hi> ye ſhall haue the
<hi>Catalogue;</hi> But this is the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>moſt</hi> bleſt of all your good workes. It was a lamentable crie in <hi>Ieruſalem, Parvuli panem petunt, &amp; nemo eſt qui frangit illis,</hi> The children crie for
<hi>bread,</hi> and there is none to giue it them, the <hi>children,</hi> the
<hi>younglings, ſucklings, babes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 4.</note> and latter <hi>births,</hi> they that could neither <hi>ſtir</hi> to
<hi>get</hi> it, nor <hi>labour</hi> to <hi>gaine</hi> it. <hi>Parvuli panem petunt,</hi> the weake ſicke, <hi>infant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent tenderlings,</hi> not able to continue faſting, nor to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour themſelues by <hi>feeding,</hi> in
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> they periſhed, nothing in the <hi>Lamentation</hi> more
<hi>lamentable:</hi> But here they are nouriſhed, bleſſed be the Lord, our <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> breſts be not drie, <hi>dearth</hi> hath not threatned <hi>death, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, bountie, mercie,</hi> had fed theſe poore
<hi>children,</hi> Gods <hi>promiſe, grace,</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> will reward it. I will not preſſe you, that are ſo gratiouſly
<hi>forward,</hi> nor tell you that <hi>ſomewhat</hi> is wanting yet, that
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was plagued, for not <hi>building</hi> of her decayed
<hi>Temple,</hi> which was the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of her <hi>Cittie,</hi> nor encite by any arguments <hi>further</hi> then <hi>Haggai</hi> inciteth you, <hi>Hagg.</hi>
1.9. I will not tell you that <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> hath not a more glorious
<hi>foundation</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14038:27"/>then you haue to worke vpon, for you are ſure to builde vpon <hi>faith</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pauls Church.</note>: All that I moue is this, that this <hi>vncleane, leprous, idolatrous</hi> place may be clenſed, no time ſo fit as the <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> the firſt time that Chriſt came into the <hi>Temple,</hi> Chriſt draue the <hi>buyers</hi> and
<hi>ſellers</hi> out of the Temple, and <hi>Rupertus</hi> tells vs it was at the <hi>Paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer.</hi> It is queſtioned, why <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> in
<hi>Luke,</hi> came to Chriſt being ſuch a <hi>ſinner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pupertus lib. <hi>5.</hi> in Iohan.</note> with a box of oin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, and anſwered <hi>vnguenta attulit quis nouit quod peccata ante Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fatt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la, ideo adducit vnguenta oderifera,</hi> Beloued yee had neede, to preſent
<hi>your ſelues to God,</hi> the many <hi>ſinkes</hi> of <hi>ſinnes</hi> in this <hi>Cittie,</hi> they onely bring the <hi>plague</hi> Gods
<hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and your <hi>danger,</hi> come not without your
<hi>ointments,</hi> kiſſe the <hi>ſonne,</hi> leaſt he be angry, and yee <hi>periſh</hi> from the <hi>right-way, offer</hi> ſweete
<hi>ointments,</hi> and in a <hi>ſweete</hi> place, ſanctifie <hi>your ſelues,</hi> and your <hi>ointments,</hi> and <hi>place,</hi> yee
<hi>preſent</hi> it in; A woman perfumed a <hi>Lepers</hi> houſe once, and the houſe hath <hi>ſmelt</hi> of the ſauour euer ſince, at length
<hi>perſume</hi> this place, and doe this and <hi>whatſoeuer you doe, to the glory of God:</hi> This is the <hi>this</hi> that receiueth the commendation, for this act, the <hi>Author</hi> a woman is <hi>honoured:</hi> which is my next part: This that this <hi>woman</hi> hath done.</p>
            <p>This woman,<note place="margin">A ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> 
               <hi>Euae à Diabolo mutuarit peccatum, Eue</hi> the firſt woman, tooke vp ſinne from
<hi>Sathan</hi> vpon her bare word, <hi>Adam</hi> by conſenting
<hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aduiſedly</hi> ſubſcribed to the bond, <hi>vſura creuit poſteritati</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſten,</hi> but the burthen of the
<hi>intereſt,</hi> euer ſince lay heauy on their <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie:</hi> the woman was firſt in the <hi>tranſgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion,</hi> but no wonder, for if <hi>Lucifer</hi> an <hi>Angell,</hi> firſt <hi>fell</hi> in heauen, it is not <hi>ſtrange</hi> that a <hi>woman</hi> fell in <hi>earth,</hi> in
<hi>Paradiſe</hi> was the <hi>quarrell,</hi> euer ſince was the
<hi>battle,</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> loſt the <hi>field,</hi> though the won an loſt the <hi>garden,</hi> God gaue the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the <hi>honour</hi> and the
<hi>victorie</hi> in the day of battle: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men mulieris,</hi> the
<hi>ſeede</hi> of the <hi>woman</hi> ſhall breake the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> head, all the <hi>quarrell</hi> ſince is for the broken head.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14038:27"/>
               <hi>Draw</hi> thy <hi>ſword,</hi> and ſlay mee,<note place="margin">Iudg 9.54.</note> ſaith <hi>Abimelech</hi> to his Armour-bearer, when a <hi>woman</hi> had wounded him, that they ſay not, A woman ſlew him, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.54. <hi>Sathan</hi> was as
<hi>Abimelech</hi> wounded by a <hi>woman.</hi> In all the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> yee haue ſcarce any <hi>example</hi> of any <hi>woman</hi> that wounded a man, but ſtill ſhe aimed at the <hi>head.</hi> When <hi>Iael</hi> ſlew
<hi>Siſera,</hi> ſhee nailed his <hi>head</hi> to the ground,<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.21.</note> 
               <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4 21. When <hi>Sheba</hi> rebelled, and <hi>Ioab</hi> beſieged him, a woman crieth to the
<hi>Captaine,</hi> The <hi>head</hi> of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſhall be caſt ouer to thee, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.21.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 20.21. Iudg.
13.8.</note> When <hi>Iudith</hi> ſlew <hi>Holofernes,</hi> ſhe ſmote away his <hi>head</hi> from him, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 13.8. When the woman ſlew
<hi>Abimelech,</hi> ſhe caſt a peece of a <hi>milſtone</hi> on his
<hi>head, Iudg</hi> 9.53.<note place="margin">Iudg 9.53.</note> I am neither
<hi>friend</hi> nor <hi>ſtranger</hi> to ſtrange <hi>Allegories.</hi> Theſe be <hi>ſemblances</hi> of the womans <hi>breaking</hi> the Serpents
<hi>head.</hi> But the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in my Text is anointing her <hi>Sauiours head,</hi> a worke that no <hi>woman</hi> did but <hi>ſhe,</hi> and therefore
<hi>ſhe</hi> to bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured among <hi>women.</hi> Yet who this
<hi>woman</hi> was, wee may ſooner <hi>queſtion,</hi> then <hi>know. Nec ſiue ex curioſitate, ſiue ex praeſumptione, diſquirere cupiamus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Kemnitius:</hi> and his counſell is good,<note place="margin">Kemnitius hanu. Euang. in bunc locum.</note>
               <hi>preſumption</hi> and <hi>curioſitie</hi> in queſtions are to be auoided; yet the <hi>Truth</hi> is ſo to bee embraced, as that
<hi>negligently</hi> to refuſe <hi>knowledge,</hi> is a dull
<hi>ſuperſtition.</hi> The wiſe ſhould neither bee <hi>Scepticks,</hi> nor <hi>Guoſticks: Curioſitie</hi> is dangerous, <hi>Ignorance</hi> is odious. <hi>Oculos habemus Talparum, non Aquilarum:</hi> It is true, and it is our <hi>miſerie;</hi> yet to haue no <hi>eyes,</hi> or hauing, to ſtop our
<hi>eyes,</hi> is baſe blindfolded <hi>Idolatrie. Maries</hi> face is not as
<hi>Moyſes</hi> face, it hath no <hi>vaile,</hi> wee may looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and aske, <hi>Magdalen,</hi> art thou <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſiſter, or ſhall wee looke for another? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlgatiſſima opinio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kemnitius.</note> ſaith <hi>Kemnitius, ipſam fuiſſe peccatricem illam:</hi> It was the moſt commonly knowne opinion, that this
<hi>woman</hi> was the ſinner in <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpell. And howſoeuer ſome thinke that the thrice anointing of Chriſt was performed by three
<hi>women,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roffenſ. de tribus Magdalenis.</note> which
<hi>Roffenſis</hi> (the Beau-clarke of his time)
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14038:28"/>confuteth in three bookes, yet the generall ſtreame of all <hi>antiquitie,</hi> and the opinion of the <hi>Church,</hi> (as <hi>Roffenſis</hi> by impregnable <hi>arguments</hi> proueth) is this,
<hi>vnicam eſſe Magdalenam, candem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> bis vnxiſſe Chriſtum.</hi> It is a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed</hi> and <hi>perplexed</hi> queſtion, I confeſſe,
<hi>&amp; plus ſubtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis quàm vtilitatis habens,</hi> as
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſpake: and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeue it be none of thoſe
<hi>Cobwebs,</hi> wherein ſome Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh flies haue beene <hi>caught</hi> by their <hi>cunning,</hi> yet may it ſeeme as <hi>intorteled</hi> and
<hi>intangled</hi> a queſtion, as any in the <hi>Harmony</hi> of the Goſpell. Only I wonder that they that are ſo <hi>oppoſite</hi> in the deniall of it, take not <hi>Archidamus</hi> counſell, to bring more
<hi>ſtrength,</hi> and leſſe <hi>ſting</hi> in their argunents; this were more <hi>courage,</hi> and leſſe <hi>rage. Faber St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulenſis</hi> cals it a <hi>lie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Faber <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay.</note>
               <hi>Roffenſis</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Simendacium, profecto ſolenne mendacium &amp; celebre, imo nihil celebrius;</hi> for in the <hi>Greeke Church</hi> many beleeued (as <hi>Origen</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth in his 33. <hi>Homilie</hi> on
<hi>Matthew</hi>) that the woman that anointed our <hi>Sauiours feet</hi> in
<hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is the ſame that anointed his
<hi>head</hi> here: and howſoeuer <hi>Origen</hi> himſelfe may ſeeme
<hi>doubting</hi> herein, yet in his firſt Homilie on the <hi>Canticles</hi> he is reſolute for it, and ſo are many other of the <hi>Greeke Church. Theophiles, Seuerianus, Euſebius, Ammonius, Gregory Nazianzene,</hi> and
<hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> whom though they vouch as the chiefeſt of the
<hi>Weſterne Church</hi> againſt,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> yet <hi>acknowledgeth</hi> it in his Homilie on the treaſon of
<hi>Iudas.</hi> All the foure <hi>Latine Fathers</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this;
<hi>Hierome</hi> in his Proeme vpon <hi>Oſea, Ambroſe</hi> in his
<hi>Comment</hi> vpon <hi>Luke, Gregory</hi> in his <hi>Morals,</hi> and <hi>S Auſtine</hi> reconciling the <hi>Euangeliſts,</hi> thus; <hi>Ego quidem nihil aliud intelligendum arbitror, niſi quod non aliam fuiſſe muliere in quae peccatrix tum acceſſit ad pedes Ieſu, ſed can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Mariam bis hoc feciſſe. Beda</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> and many others, all the
<hi>Schoolemen,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Albertus</hi> and <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> moſt confident in it. <hi>Albertus</hi> vpon the 7. of <hi>Luke,</hi> hauing repeated the <hi>oppoſite Authors,</hi> concludeth, <hi>Et ſic procerto Deus fecit duo luminariamagna, duas Marias, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14038:28"/>ſcilicet Domini, &amp; ſororem Lazari, quam &amp; pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricem fuiſſe conſtat. Aquinas</hi> on the 12. of
<hi>Iohn</hi> reciteth and confuteth the contrary arguments, and therein and in other places concludeth this woman to be that <hi>Mary the ſinner,</hi> that
<hi>anointed</hi> his <hi>feet</hi> in <hi>Luke</hi> as a <hi>Sinner,</hi> and now <hi>anointeth</hi> his <hi>head</hi> as a <hi>Saint.</hi> To theſe I might adde <hi>a cloud of witneſſes,</hi> which if they were not thought
<hi>clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> might cleare the <hi>point.</hi> But I know this
<hi>time</hi> and <hi>place</hi> is vnfit for <hi>Paradox.</hi> To affirme
<hi>raſhly,</hi> were <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorie;</hi> to denie <hi>reſolutely,</hi> were <hi>follie.</hi> This is a <hi>wanton Age,</hi> and we rather bring the
<hi>eares</hi> of <hi>curioſitie,</hi> then the <hi>hearts</hi> of
<hi>obedience:</hi> With the <hi>Athenians,</hi> wee aske for <hi>newes;</hi> but with the <hi>Bereans,</hi> we ſhould ſearch the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> The moſt probable argument that is brought to confirme this <hi>doubt</hi> in
<hi>queſtion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.2.</note> is out of
<hi>Iohn</hi> 11.2. where the act of <hi>anointing</hi> Chriſt, and the name of her <hi>perſon</hi> is mentioned. It was that <hi>Mary</hi> which anointed the <hi>Lord</hi> with <hi>ointment,</hi> and <hi>wiped</hi> his <hi>feet</hi> with her <hi>haires,</hi> whoſe brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> was ſicke. Here is one <hi>anointing</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh.
12.3.</note> In <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.3. there is another mention of
<hi>anointing,</hi> Then tooke <hi>Mary</hi> a pound of <hi>ointment,</hi> of
<hi>Spikenard,</hi> very coſtly, and <hi>anointed</hi> the <hi>feet</hi> of
<hi>Ieſus,</hi> and wiped his <hi>feet</hi> with her <hi>haire. Faber</hi> and others anſwer, both theſe are one, the firſt related by
<hi>anticipation,</hi> vſuall in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> when a thing is ſpoken of as <hi>done,</hi> before it be done. <hi>Roffenſis</hi> anſwers,<note place="margin">Roffenſ. de tribus Magdalenis.</note> that in all <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Goſpell there is not one <hi>anticipation,</hi> howſoeuer in other <hi>Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts</hi> ſome few, yet in <hi>Iohn</hi> none, nothing related by the tenſe of the <hi>time paſt,</hi> that was to bee <hi>future,</hi> at that time not <hi>finiſhed. Iohn</hi> 12.4. he ſpeaketh of <hi>Iudas, Iudas qui traditurus, non qui tradidit:</hi> Againe,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 6.71. <hi>Iudas qui traditurus, non qui tradidit. Iohn</hi> 7.39.
<hi>Hoc dixit de Spiritu quem eſſent accepturi, non quem accepiſſent:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.2. he ſpeakes of
<hi>Mary</hi> in the <hi>Participle</hi> of the time paſt,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Beza</hi> renders, <hi>Vnxit, exterſit,</hi> ſhe had <hi>anointed,</hi> ſhe had <hi>wiped,</hi> as done
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14038:29"/>already, and after in <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.2. mentions that other <hi>anointing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.2.</note> Arguments of probabilitie there may bee many: Shee that in <hi>Luke</hi> anointed <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> ſo our laſt
<hi>Interpreters</hi> in the contents of the ſeuenth chapter tell vs, the
<hi>fire</hi> of her <hi>affection</hi> ſtrangely <hi>inflamed</hi> her
<hi>heart</hi> in her <hi>loue</hi> to her <hi>Lord.</hi> Chriſt giueth her this teſtimonie, <hi>She loued much;</hi> and whoſe loue to Chriſt was euer ſo <hi>regiſtred</hi> as the loue of <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſiſter? Is it <hi>probable,</hi> I ſay is it <hi>poſſible,</hi> that ſhe that ſo
<hi>loued</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> ſhould neither at his
<hi>paſſion,</hi> nor after his <hi>paſſion,</hi> nor in his
<hi>reſurrection,</hi> afford any token in her <hi>weeping,</hi> hauing loſt whom ſhe <hi>loued,</hi> or by <hi>watching</hi> to finde whom ſhe
<hi>loſt?</hi> In all the foure <hi>Euangelists,</hi> no word of <hi>Mary, Lazarus</hi> ſiſter, at the <hi>paſſion,</hi> or after the
<hi>paſſion,</hi> or in his <hi>reſurrection,</hi> vnleſſe it be by the name of <hi>Mary Magdalen. Lazarus</hi> ſiſter was frequent in
<hi>weeping,</hi> went to <hi>Lazarus</hi> graue <hi>weeping,</hi> came and fell downe before Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.33. <hi>weeping,</hi> and who more
<hi>aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> in <hi>teares</hi> then <hi>Mary Magdalen?</hi> not only in the houſe of <hi>Simon,</hi> where ſhe not only <hi>wet,</hi> but
<hi>waſht</hi> Chriſts feet with <hi>teares,</hi> but her <hi>teares</hi> at the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> at <hi>graue,</hi> at <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> her
<hi>eyes</hi> ſeeming to be the <hi>Cymbals</hi> of her <hi>ſorrow,</hi> all things inuiting her to the <hi>wofull exerciſe</hi> of <hi>weeping.</hi> Adde hereunto, that whenſoeuer <hi>Mary, Lazarus</hi> ſiſter, came to Chriſt, ſhe fell at his <hi>feet:</hi> ſo did <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. Lazarus</hi> ſiſter vſually called Chriſt <hi>Maſter;</hi> The
<hi>Maſter</hi> is come, ſaith <hi>Martha</hi> to <hi>Mary, Iohn</hi>
11.28. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> comming to ſeeke her <hi>Sauiour</hi> at the
<hi>Sepulchre,</hi> Chriſt calling her <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhe anſwereth by the former word <hi>Maſter:</hi> both <hi>followed</hi> him, both
<hi>frequently heard</hi> him, both <hi>anointed</hi> him in the houſe of
<hi>Simon,</hi> as the <hi>Goſpell</hi> teſtifieth both in the houſe of the ſame <hi>Simon,</hi> in the ſame <hi>place,</hi> at <hi>Bethany,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> collecteth, both brought boxes of <hi>Alablaſter,</hi> both <hi>wiped</hi> with their <hi>haire,</hi> both <hi>actions</hi> commended; and therefore it is moſt <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,</hi> that both were
<hi>performed</hi> by the ſame <hi>woman,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14038:29"/>otherwiſe it ſhould ſeeme
<hi>ſtrange,</hi> that this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſhould make this
<hi>mention</hi> of this act of this <hi>woman,</hi> with this
<hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne</hi> memoriall, and wee ſhould bee <hi>vncertaine</hi> who this woman is. I ſubmit theſe collections to the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend,</hi> and
<hi>learned:</hi> The <hi>Cynicke</hi> will not be ſatisfied, the
<hi>Scepticke</hi> cannot, and for the Curious querulous <hi>Pioner</hi> that onely brings his <hi>eares,</hi> not his <hi>heart,</hi> I deſire neither to
<hi>pleaſe,</hi> nor <hi>eaſily</hi> to <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> him. All I ſay is <hi>this,</hi> there be bleſſed <hi>ſeruants</hi> of God of both
<hi>opinions, opinion</hi> is no <hi>determination,</hi> it is no
<hi>article</hi> of our <hi>faith, fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi> is
<hi>blinde</hi> in the beſt things: we ſee but in <hi>part,</hi> wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie but in <hi>part.</hi> Onely I <hi>wonder</hi> that this loud ſoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding ſolemne Propheſie of this Goſpell, and this work and this
<hi>woman</hi> ſhould be ſo ſtifled, and <hi>ſtrangled,</hi> by the
<hi>crooked</hi> lines of <hi>contrary</hi> Interpreters. This woman ſaith my Text, from whom as from the <hi>wombe</hi> of my Text we receiue this
<hi>Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> the Lord giueth much
<hi>honour</hi> to the <hi>woman</hi> as to the <hi>weaker veſſell,</hi> in that his <hi>ſpirit</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth the leaſt holy duties performed by women: the Reaſon, is to manifeſt that as the woman was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of
<hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> ſo by Chriſt ſhee is made toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>coheire</hi> of the grace of life. Sure Gods Spirit hath ſome eſpeciall end in it, to giue comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to that weake ſex, by taking an
<hi>Inuentory</hi> of the <hi>particular</hi> acts in Scripture, performed by
<hi>women,</hi> not onely the <hi>chamber</hi> prouided by the
<hi>Sunamite</hi> for the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi> 2 King. 4.10. but a <hi>nights lodging</hi> afforded <hi>Ioſhuas</hi> ſpies,<note place="margin">2 King
4.10.</note> by the Inne-keeper <hi>Rahab,<note place="margin">Ioſh.
2.1.</note> Ioſh.</hi> 2.1. and a ſmall meaſure of oyle and meale, by the widdow to <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 Kings 17.14. theſe are vpon record and looſe not their reward, <hi>Magdalens</hi> box, <hi>Maries</hi> choice,<note place="margin">1 King. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>Marthaes</hi> cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full entertainment, the <hi>Sulamite, Sunamite, Caananite,</hi> the woman of <hi>Samariahs</hi> pitcher, the poore <hi>widdowes</hi> mite, are not forgotten, which is
<hi>enough</hi> to put the <hi>life</hi> of religion into the <hi>hearts</hi> of women, to ſee euery little <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of theirs ſo well accepted. And ſure many of them,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14038:30"/>haue beene both <hi>partakers</hi> of great mercy, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Gods glory,</hi> as in their owne
<hi>lifes,</hi> which as <hi>lamps</hi> gaue light to their <hi>vnbeleeuing Huſbands,</hi> ſo in gouerning their <hi>familie,</hi> and in inſtructing their <hi>children,</hi> ſo was <hi>Bathſheba</hi> a bleſſed mother to
<hi>Salomon, Loys</hi> to <hi>Timothy, Maxima</hi> to <hi>Baſill, Monica</hi> to <hi>Auſtin, Pulcheria</hi> to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius, Helena</hi> to
<hi>Conſtantine:</hi> in the ſex where ſinne hath abounded, Grace hath ſuperabounded: But none of all that <hi>ſex,</hi> the bleſſed Virgin onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hitherto euer receiued ſuch an <hi>honour</hi> as this
<hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> many <hi>daughters</hi> haue done vertuouſly, <hi>but thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleſt them all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31.</note> I deny not but
<hi>Sathan</hi> that blaſted <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,</hi> hath much blemiſhed the
<hi>honour</hi> of this ſex, hee made choice of a <hi>woman,</hi> to bee the firſt <hi>engine,</hi> and in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> by this wheele he turned about the <hi>world,</hi> and ſince <hi>Dalila</hi> was the trappe for
<hi>Sampſon,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for <hi>Salomon, Ieſabell</hi> for <hi>Ahab,</hi> almoſt all the <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies,</hi> though <hi>fathered</hi> by <hi>men,</hi> yet <hi>furthered</hi> by
<hi>womens</hi> wit, <hi>Helena</hi> furthers <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſtratagem,
<hi>Phioume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> her <hi>Apelles, Montanus</hi> hath his <hi>Priſca, Donatus</hi> his <hi>Lucilla, Priſcillinus</hi> his <hi>Galla, Arius</hi> aſſiſted by <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> ſiſter, and <hi>Nicholas</hi> the <hi>Deacon</hi> hath a conſort of ſuch <hi>Companions;</hi> and of all Creatures that euer GOD <hi>created,</hi> there bee no ſuch
<hi>enſnaring</hi> attractiue <hi>loadſtones</hi> and
<hi>loadſtarres</hi> to Superſtition and <hi>Idolatry</hi> as women. Yet as
<hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpake of the <hi>figges,</hi> the good <hi>figges</hi> were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 24.3.</note> and the <hi>euill</hi> were very <hi>euill, Ier.</hi> 24.3. So the good <hi>women</hi> are very
<hi>good,</hi> and ſuch were thoſe holy <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in old time, who
<hi>truſted in God.</hi> And as the <hi>Deuill</hi> neuer found of ſuch an
<hi>engine</hi> as the <hi>woman,</hi> ſo neuer ſuch an <hi>enemie</hi> aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt him as the <hi>woman: Piumſane, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and
<hi>pittifull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> and ſanctified is this ſex, ſaith <hi>Auſten,</hi> and the <hi>honour</hi> done by our Sauiour vnto them, hath much <hi>exalted the humble and meeke;</hi> for beſides that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin</hi> concceiued him, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the houſe
<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied</hi> of him, euery <hi>paſſage</hi> of his life had ſome <hi>women</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14038:30"/>to attend him. <hi>Hanna</hi> in the
<hi>Temple</hi> reioyced to ſee him, and <hi>Magdalen</hi> at the
<hi>table</hi> waſht and annointed him, and <hi>Martha</hi> with a great feaſt entertained him, and <hi>Mary</hi> her <hi>Siſter</hi> poured ointment on him, and <hi>Iohanna</hi> and <hi>Suſanna</hi> and many women miniſtred of their <hi>ſubſtance</hi> to him: the <hi>Daughters</hi> of
<hi>Ieruſalem</hi> wept for him, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry <hi>women</hi> with infinite
<hi>ſorrow,</hi> attended him at the <hi>croſſe</hi> when his
<hi>Diſciples</hi> fled from him, and <hi>women</hi> came to the
<hi>graue,</hi> though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Nichodemus</hi> had beſtowed a <hi>hundred pound</hi> of Mirrh and <hi>Aloes,</hi> as well applied as
<hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Deuotion</hi> could deuiſe, yet <hi>women</hi> came to
<hi>embalme</hi> his body, and whom they found <hi>wanting</hi> to annoint, they ſought weeping to lament. This honourable <hi>teſtimonie,</hi> of this holy <hi>woman,</hi> giueth full aſſurance of <hi>our Sauiours acceptance</hi> of the ſeruice of that <hi>ſex,</hi> if they be ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſeeing hee <hi>ioynes</hi> with this <hi>Goſpell,</hi> this
<hi>woman,</hi> and this <hi>worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vſe whereof, ſhould incite all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> women to <hi>ſerue</hi> the Lord, that in the day of <hi>retribution,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> they may receiue reward from the Lord. S.
<hi>Auſten</hi> maketh this Vſe; <hi>Quum foenum eruerit, ſlos deciderit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>verbua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini manebit,</hi> when the <hi>graſſe</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> of
<hi>beauty,</hi> and the <hi>flower</hi> of mortall <hi>frailty</hi> ſhall fall, the <hi>word</hi> of the Lord ſhall <hi>endure</hi> for euer.
<hi>Chriſtian Matrones</hi> be yee <hi>ambitious</hi> of the beauty of the
<hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Zyon,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member yee that <hi>ſupercilious ſailes</hi> of <hi>vanitie</hi> and <hi>vaine glory,</hi> as they are the
<hi>vnfitting faſhion</hi> of the Court ſo the <hi>worſt infection</hi> of the <hi>Citie.</hi> Much ornament is no good <hi>ſigne,</hi> painting of the <hi>face</hi> argues an ill <hi>complexion</hi> of <hi>body,</hi> a worſe
<hi>mind: Truth</hi> hath a <hi>face</hi> both <hi>honeſt</hi> and
<hi>comely,</hi> and <hi>lookes</hi> beſt in her wone <hi>colours.</hi> The Lord <hi>threatneth</hi> in <hi>Eſay</hi> to ranſacke <hi>the womens wardrope,</hi> and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>tinkling ornaments, and their caules and round tires,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 3.</note> 
               <hi>and chaines, and bracelets, and muſters, and bonnets, and headbands, and tablets, and earnings, and mantles, and wim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Iewells, and hoods, and vailes, and criſping pinnes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14038:31"/>and threatneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſten.</note> 
               <hi>lamentation and mourning, and deſolation to thoſe daintie Creatures that ſate at eaſe in Sion: God</hi> is the ſame your <hi>ſinnes</hi> the ſame, your <hi>warning</hi> the ſame. <hi>Nuptae Suſannam, Anna vidus, virgines Mariam cogitent,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Auſten:</hi> I might remember you how hatefull the memorie of ſome women are, a <hi>Diblaim</hi> or <hi>Dido, Infaelix Dido, nulls bene nupta, marito:</hi> Such are the ſexes <hi>curſe,</hi> and the earths
<hi>dregges</hi> of <hi>corruption.</hi> I might remember you, of our
<hi>Debora,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Elizabeth</hi> a woman after Gods owne heart, the glory of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and enuie of the <hi>Infidell</hi> world, who was ſuch a <hi>nurſing</hi> mother to our <hi>Land</hi> and
<hi>Church,</hi> that the cauſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> doth owe more to that one <hi>Queene,</hi> then to many <hi>Kings</hi> that were before her. But the time as well as the <hi>feaſt</hi> keeps <hi>Paſſouer,</hi> and I follow. All <hi>women</hi> muſt needs confeſſe that they can neuer
<hi>honour</hi> him enough who hath <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> them ſo farre, as to make them the firſt <hi>witneſſes</hi> of his
<hi>reſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo.</note> and hath as
<hi>Hugo</hi> obſerueth <hi>principally</hi> deſerued the loue of
<hi>women</hi> in that hee vouchſafed to be borne of a <hi>woman,</hi> that when it was granted to no <hi>man,</hi> to be the <hi>father,</hi> it was performed to a <hi>woman,</hi> to bee the <hi>mother</hi> of Chriſt: wherefore ye <hi>Ladies,</hi> which like the <hi>lyllies</hi> of the
<hi>field,</hi> toile not, nor <hi>ſpinne</hi> not, and yet <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in all his royaltie not arraied as one of <hi>theſe.</hi> If euer yee had
<hi>pitty</hi> on the <hi>fruite</hi> of your <hi>wombes,</hi> take
<hi>pittie</hi> on your <hi>ſoules,</hi> pamper not your <hi>bodies</hi> to murther your <hi>ſoules.</hi> Cloath not <hi>Hagar</hi> with the colour of the <hi>Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> and let <hi>Sara,</hi> the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the Kings daughter ſterue. Flatter not your ſelue, <hi>worms</hi> made your
<hi>cloathes, worms</hi> eate your <hi>bodies.</hi> Alas <hi>wantons,</hi> and
<hi>wormes-meate,</hi> what be yee? what ſhall become of yee, if ye neglect the <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of ſaluation?</hi> No oyle for your lampes! no ointment for your heads; <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſhould become the <hi>houſe</hi> of God for euer, if ye are <hi>his,</hi> ye are <hi>his houſes,</hi> to dwell in, and nothing can better become yee then <hi>holineſſe. Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie natures frailtie, affections fancie</hi> cannot better become
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14038:31"/>yee. <hi>Apparell, nakedneſſe garment, follies garniſh, Adams fig-leaues, and beaſts leauings,</hi> cannot better become yee: <hi>Gold and ſiluer, the Wiſe-mans droſſe, but the Miſerables darling, the earths gifts, and mineralls garbage,</hi> cannot better become ye; <hi>Wit, vertues wanton, fooles wonder, vices friend, and the worlds fauorite,</hi> cannot better become ye. Embrace, annoint, kiſſe, loue, ſolace, onely in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation</hi> of your ſauiour. No
<hi>ſnake</hi> in this <hi>garden,</hi> no <hi>worme</hi> in that
<hi>gourd,</hi> be ye amiable as <hi>Rahell,</hi> wiſe as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca,</hi> obedient as <hi>Sara,</hi> diligent as <hi>Martha,</hi> but withall religious as <hi>Mary</hi> who receiued this Teſtimonie, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</hi> I am at length come to her <hi>memoriall:</hi> my third circumſtance of the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saint Chryſoſtome</hi> makes mention,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>hom.</hi> 14.</note> of the women of <hi>Corinth,</hi> who had a cuſtome to ſet vp <hi>lights</hi> or
<hi>tapers</hi> at the birth of euery childe, with <hi>proper names,</hi> and looke what name the <hi>taper</hi> bare which laſted longeſt in the
<hi>burning,</hi> they transferred that name to the <hi>childe:</hi> our Lord hath put vp a <hi>burning lampe</hi> for a perpetuall <hi>monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of
<hi>Mary,</hi> her <hi>name,</hi> and her <hi>ointment</hi> ſhall neuer haue an end, <hi>Quanto huius ſeminis benedictio ſatio parca, meſſis abundans Auguſta vena, ſpatioſi maris, quantum pretium praetioſae meris.</hi> No <hi>Iuſtes,</hi> nor <hi>Olympiads,</hi> nor <hi>Iubiles,</hi> nor <hi>ages,</hi> nor <hi>Plato</hi> his longeſt yeare, nor the long liued mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ninth <hi>ſpheare,</hi> ſhall <hi>terminate,</hi> or
<hi>antiquate,</hi> this memoriall. In this <hi>Goſpell</hi> I ſhould looke
<hi>for a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> vpon Chriſts <hi>ſepulcher:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay</note> It was <hi>Eſaies</hi> Propheſie <hi>glorioſum erit eius ſepulchru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Alexander</hi> may haue <hi>Europe</hi> and
<hi>Aſia,</hi> and all the world repreſented on his <hi>Tombe, Cyrus</hi> on his, <hi>Hic Perſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domitor, Themiſtocles</hi> on his, <hi>En memoranda facta Themiſtocles,</hi> yet neither <hi>Alexander</hi> againſt
<hi>Barbarians, Themiſtocles</hi> againſt the <hi>Perſians, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milius</hi> againſt the <hi>Macedonians, Marcellus</hi> againſt the <hi>Scithians,</hi> or <hi>Scipio</hi> againſt the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> had euer the like victory in the <hi>field,</hi> as Chriſt had in the <hi>graue,</hi> nor doth this <hi>victorie</hi> want a memory <hi>euer vpon</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14038:32"/>of his <hi>Sepulchre.</hi> For as
<hi>Alphonſus</hi> had this, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus iacet hic,</hi> ſo Chriſts Sepulcher this <hi>inſcription, Luk</hi> 24.6. <hi>Surrexit Chriſtus, noneſt hic.</hi> That memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all is by an Angell, but Chriſts
<hi>memoriall</hi> is by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe: A more ample
<hi>memoriall</hi> then euer Chriſt gaue <hi>any,</hi> neither <hi>Peter</hi> firſt called, nor <hi>Iohn</hi> beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, nor <hi>Iames</hi> his neere kinſman, none of theſe pillars as <hi>Paul</hi> calleth them had ſuch a
<hi>Pillar</hi> erected as <hi>Maries</hi> memoriall, Chriſt buildeth a memoriall out of <hi>Maries</hi> box, becauſe ſhe poured her <hi>oyle</hi> on his body, and this is a memoriall, not of him, but of her:
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> obſerueth that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a ſolemne
<hi>monument,</hi> an honourable <hi>memoriall: Chryſoſtome</hi> on
<hi>Mathew</hi> wonders at the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie of this memoriall, <hi>nec inſignis perſona, nec multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine teſtium celebrata, nec in Templo, nec in Theatro, ſed in domo, &amp; in domo leproſi confecta,</hi> No noble
<hi>perſonage,</hi> not done in the <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Theatre,</hi> or before a <hi>multitude</hi> of witneſſes, but in a <hi>priuate</hi> houſe, in the houſe of a <hi>Leper,</hi> when the Diſciples were onely preſent, and yet ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the famous deedes of Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours is ſilenced, they which built <hi>cities,</hi> erected wals, fought battles, attained <hi>Trophies,</hi> ſubdued <hi>nations,</hi> though they erected <hi>ſtatues,</hi> and made <hi>ordinances,</hi> for celebrating
<hi>their memorialls,</hi> yet their <hi>memoriall</hi> is periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, when as this act of this woman, is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and this is the woman whoſe praiſe is in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. A <hi>priuate woman,</hi> in a
<hi>priuate</hi> manner, in the <hi>priuate</hi> houſe of a <hi>Leper</hi> to poure out a <hi>ſmall</hi> box of <hi>ointment</hi> on Chriſts head. Say her <hi>loue</hi> was great, and her act was <hi>good,</hi> and her oyntment were <hi>pretious,</hi> notwithſtanding that of <hi>Claudian,</hi> in greater acts hath beene true, <hi>Minuit preſentia famam quanto magis illam minuit notitia:</hi> Fame is an <hi>infection,</hi> acts <hi>reported</hi> are either
<hi>portentious,</hi> beyond truth, and by bigneſſe they <hi>breake,</hi> or elſe ſo <hi>cankered</hi> with the <hi>ruſt</hi> of <hi>vntruth,</hi> as being <hi>leſſened</hi> they <hi>liue</hi> not. It is true many haue
<hi>ſought honour</hi> by building, wherein
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14038:32"/>they haue thought to leaue perpetuall
<hi>monuments,</hi> and what are all theſe, but <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mons ryots,</hi> and
<hi>times ruines,</hi> making the <hi>earth</hi> to groane vnder the
<hi>burthen</hi> it bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Where is <hi>Neroes</hi> houſe of gold, or
<hi>Diocleſians</hi> hot bathes, or <hi>Anthonies</hi> water workes, or
<hi>Auguſtus</hi> forum, or <hi>Cornelius</hi> Theatre, or the
<hi>Amphitheatre</hi> of <hi>Statilius,</hi> or <hi>Dianas</hi> Temple, or the
<hi>Manſolian</hi> Tombe, or <hi>Octanias</hi> gate, or <hi>Liuias</hi> gally, or <hi>Apolloes</hi> Church, or <hi>Iupiters</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll? It is a very poore monument, how immenſe, how ſound that lime, and ſtone, and wood, and timber, and duſt, and aſhes, muſt pile for a <hi>memoriall</hi> to <hi>poſteritie,</hi> when time, and ſtorme, and winde, and weather, and moath, and ruſt, and ruine doe corrupt it. There was a monument beſtowed on a Viceroy of <hi>Spaine, Propter nos &amp; noſtram ſalutem, deſcendit ad inferos:</hi> and many ſuch great ones, to the ſhame of their
<hi>poſteritie</hi> deſerue no better <hi>memorie.</hi> When as
<hi>Maries</hi> ointment ſmels ſweete ouer all the world, whoſe memoriall yeelds this <hi>Doctrine, The good workes of Gods Saints, ſhall bee had in euerlaſting remembrance.</hi> The reaſon,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> becauſe they ſhall bee <hi>exemplary</hi> to <hi>poſteritie,</hi> and incitements to <hi>Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> In <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 3. there is a liſt of the <hi>Benefactours</hi> that built the <hi>wall</hi> of
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 3.</note> not onely their
<hi>families</hi> and their <hi>Tribes,</hi> but their <hi>trades,</hi> the
<hi>Marchants,</hi> and the <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> are twiſe named, the whole
<hi>trade</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> are named, and one, in the 8. verſe, and
<hi>Apothe earies</hi> ſonne is named, and after ſeuerall men, and euery mans <hi>ſeuerall worke.</hi> The <hi>righteous</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall be had in euerlaſting <hi>remembrance, Pſal.</hi> 112.6
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, bleſſed and long liued ſaith
<hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Bleſſings are on the <hi>head</hi> of the Iuſt, the <hi>memory</hi> of the iuſt is <hi>bleſſed,</hi> Pro. 10.7. the remembrance of <hi>Ioſias</hi> as the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>perfume,</hi> Eccleſ. 49.1. The heathen thought for euer to be remembred, for their famous inuentions, <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> for letters, <hi>Pithagoras</hi> for numbers,
<hi>Sidonius</hi> for mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> for medicines,
<hi>Lycurgus</hi> for Lawes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14038:33"/>
               <hi>Arte</hi> for arts, <hi>Hercules</hi> for games, but how few take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this <hi>fame,</hi> when that the godly
<hi>neglected</hi> on earth are regiſtred in <hi>heauen,</hi> and emblaſond by Gods <hi>ſentence</hi> and ſanction. <hi>Non ſic impij, non ſic,</hi> the vngodly are not ſo, they <hi>periſh,</hi> and
<hi>ſtinke,</hi> and <hi>rot,</hi> the countenance of the Lord is againſt them, to roote out their <hi>remembrance from the earth,</hi> Pſal. 34.15.
<hi>vt puluis platearum, lutum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tearum, lanugo plantarum, vt limus, fumus, feſtuca, patea, ſpuma,</hi> as chaffe of the ſloore, duſt of the ſtreete, moſſe of the trees, droſſe of the <hi>ſiluer,</hi> foame of the <hi>ſea,</hi> froath, ſmoake, vapours, meteors, and moſt
<hi>momentany</hi> things, whereas the godly are euer <hi>honoured,</hi> their
<hi>gratious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons honoured,</hi> their <hi>glorious</hi> examples imitated. It were honour <hi>enough</hi> for good men, if they were onely
<hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> for Gods <hi>bleſſing</hi> and <hi>bountie</hi> vpon them in this life, that they are, as <hi>ſignets</hi> on his <hi>finger, ſtarres</hi> in his <hi>hand, apples</hi> of his eye, that they ſhall
<hi>ſlouriſh</hi> as the <hi>Bay-tree,</hi> the <hi>Oliue,</hi> the
<hi>Myrh,</hi> the <hi>Palme,</hi> the <hi>Cedar</hi> of <hi>Lebanus;</hi> that their names bee in <hi>heauen,</hi> Luk. 10.20. their <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in his booke, Pſalm. 139.19. their meate commeth from his hand, Pſalm. 145.15. their bones <hi>kept</hi> by him Pſal. 34.21. Their <hi>haires</hi> numbred by him, Math. 10.30. Their <hi>teares</hi> reſerued with him,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.7. But that no good <hi>worke,</hi> ſhall paſſe vnrewarded by him, not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>meate</hi> to his <hi>Prophet,</hi> or a
<hi>nights-lodging</hi> to a ſpie, or a little ointment, or a cuppe of cold water, or a <hi>mite</hi> miſſe a <hi>reward,</hi> or <hi>monument;</hi> for wee had not heard of the <hi>poores</hi> treaſury in the <hi>Temple,</hi> had not the poore <hi>widdow</hi> caſt in her mite into the
<hi>treaſurie,</hi> which mite is treaſured vp, and hath a
<hi>mention,</hi> as is this worke of this woman in this Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The vſe whereof ſhould <hi>confound,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> at leaſt <hi>confute</hi> the miſerable
<hi>mucke-wormes</hi> and penurious <hi>money-mongers,</hi> who neuer did any good, <hi>arreſtable</hi> to God, <hi>auaileable</hi> to their ſoule,
<hi>profitable</hi> to their neighbour, that came <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> into the world, and will goe <hi>naked</hi> out of the world,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14038:33"/>whoſe only <hi>godlineſſe</hi> is
<hi>gaine,</hi> who doe <hi>baſe homage</hi> to that which ſhould be the
<hi>baſeſt drudge,</hi> who are ſo farre from being <hi>guiltie</hi> of doing good, that for ſmall <hi>aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> they will be content to loſe all <hi>friends,</hi> to pine their <hi>bodies,</hi> and damne their
<hi>ſoules.</hi> Is it poſſible (had not <hi>Sathan</hi> poſſeſſed theſe <hi>ſeruile ſlaues</hi>) that a humane ſoule ſhould liue in a body ſo baſe, which makes a <hi>liueleſſe</hi> peece of earth his God? <hi>Cultor Mammonae, ſeruus pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, ſectator auaritiae; pro pecunia Hypocrita, in pecunia Apoſtolus, ex pecunia Idololatra;</hi> who like a true <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> turnes euery thing into
<hi>ſiluer,</hi> both what he ſhould <hi>eat,</hi> and what he ſhould
<hi>weare;</hi> and that hee <hi>keepes,</hi> is to <hi>looke vpon,</hi> not to
<hi>vſe,</hi> which he <hi>feares</hi> to keepe, and <hi>abhorres</hi> to loſe, who as hee <hi>liues</hi> without <hi>loue,</hi> ſo <hi>dies</hi> without <hi>teares,</hi> without <hi>pitie,</hi> ſaue that they ſay it was
<hi>pitie</hi> he died no ſooner. What ſhall become of theſe that
<hi>protect</hi> what they <hi>worſhip,</hi> and <hi>want</hi> what they
<hi>abound</hi> in? They ſhall <hi>periſh,</hi> their <hi>memoriall</hi> ſhall <hi>periſh,</hi> and well were it, if as their <hi>bodies</hi> periſh, ſo their <hi>ſoules</hi> might ſo <hi>periſh</hi> as to be no more. But how truly ſhould it poſſeſſe your <hi>ſoules</hi> with
<hi>ioy,</hi> bleſſed and beloued, who haue <hi>fed,</hi> and
<hi>cloathed,</hi> and <hi>cured,</hi> and <hi>viſited,</hi> the
<hi>weake</hi> ſicke mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus?</hi> Your almes is come vp before <hi>God,</hi> and as the <hi>ſmoake</hi> of the
<hi>Incenſe,</hi> from the <hi>Cenſor</hi> of the <hi>Angell,</hi> or the
<hi>Golden Altar,</hi> before the <hi>Throne.</hi> Yee faithfull
<hi>Deputies</hi> of your <hi>Maſter,</hi> bleſſed are yee, great is your
<hi>reward</hi> in heauen, you that are the truſtie <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers</hi> of the poore and <hi>needie,</hi> and all yee the approued <hi>Gouernours</hi> of the <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> of this Citie, ye are the <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Legacie,</hi> which was only this, <hi>The poore yee ſhall haue alwayes with you:</hi> for when hee <hi>bequeathed</hi> his <hi>Church</hi> to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and his <hi>garments</hi> to his <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,</hi> his <hi>mother</hi> to <hi>Iohn,</hi> and his <hi>body</hi> to
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but the <hi>poore</hi> he commended to his <hi>Church,</hi> and you are ſome of his <hi>executors,</hi> and haue the <hi>poore alwayes with you.</hi> It is the ſpeech of <hi>Bonauerture, Hoc piarum mentium eſt, vt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14038:34"/>nihil ſibi tribuant:</hi> It is the propertie of holy mindes, that they attribute nothing to themſelues, but onely to the
<hi>grace of God.</hi> I would not blaſt you with an infectious breath of
<hi>flatterie,</hi> or with this <hi>pretious balme</hi> breake your
<hi>heads;</hi> nor would I be ſparing to giue your <hi>memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> what God hath allowed you, ſeeing you are ſo <hi>free</hi> in paying thoſe
<hi>Legacies</hi> that Chriſt hath <hi>appointed</hi> you. It is no ſmall
<hi>honour</hi> to be one of the <hi>Maſters</hi> of an <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: Stephen</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt
<hi>Martyr,</hi> and firſt <hi>Deacon,</hi> was no other then
<hi>Treaſurer</hi> for the <hi>poore: Paul</hi> was <hi>Collector</hi> for the <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe <hi>Ouerſeer</hi> for the <hi>poore;</hi> for our <hi>Sauiour</hi> euer comming into the
<hi>Temple,</hi> caſt his eye to ſee what was caſt into the
<hi>Treaſurie</hi> for the <hi>poore.</hi> It ſhould be no ſmall
<hi>ioy</hi> to your <hi>ſoules,</hi> to conſider that God vouchſafeth the name of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> to Almes-deeds:<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iuſtus. Miſericors. Hier.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.9. <hi>Hee hath diſperſed and giuen to the poore, his righteouſneſſe endureth for euer.</hi> So <hi>S. Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſeth it, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 9.9. where the <hi>fruit</hi> of
<hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> is eſteemed <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and is aſſured of an eternall <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall.</hi> You, and your
<hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> and your <hi>Almes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and your
<hi>Almes-houſes,</hi> ſhall be had in euerlaſting <hi>remembrance.</hi> He that hath left this <hi>woman</hi> for this <hi>worke</hi> this
<hi>memoriall,</hi> I doubt not but his gratious preſence is with vs, his bleſſed <hi>eyes</hi> ouer vs, his ſacred <hi>eares</hi> open vnto vs, this <hi>morning</hi> to heare this <hi>memoriall</hi> of your bounty and mercy, and to receiue this account of the <hi>Talents</hi> that this yeere he hath truſted you with.</p>
            <list>
               <item>CHildren kept at this preſent at charges in Chriſts Hoſpitall, in the houſe, diuers places in the Citie, and with ſundry nurſes in the Country—736</item>
               <item>Children put forth Apprentiſes, diſcharged and dead this yeare out of Chriſts Hoſpitall.—59</item>
               <item>There hath bin cured this yeare paſt in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <hi>Bartholmewes</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14038:34"/>Hoſpitall, of Souldiers &amp; other diſeaſed people.—512</item>
               <item>There is in the ſaid Hoſpitall vnder cure at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.—235</item>
               <item>There hath beene cured this yeare paſt in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall, of Souldiers &amp; other diſeaſed people.—826</item>
               <item>There is in the ſaid Hoſpitall vnder cure at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent—236</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A report for Bridewell.</head>
               <p>THere hath been brought to the Hoſpitall of Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well within the ſpace of one yeare laſt paſt, of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſouldiers and other vagrant people, which haue beene paſſed thence into their natiue Countries by paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports (according to the Law in that caſe prouided) to the number of
1810. of whom many haue beene char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable to the ſaid Hoſpitall in their dyet, for the time of their being in the ſame, ſome more, ſome leſſe, as they might thence be conueniently remoued, beſides other helps there miniſtred vnto many of them, as cauſe required: <hi>viz.</hi> in hoſe, ſhooes, ſhirts, bands, money, and ſuch like, which cannot be auoided by reaſon of their miſery, nor they thence paſſed without charge to the ſaid Hoſpitall, in reſpect they are to be examined, and conſidered of, to what Countrey to bee tranſported. Alſo there is in the ſaid Hoſpitall maintained and kept in Arts and occupations, and other ſeruile workes and labours, at the charges of the ſaid Hoſpitall, of men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and children, to the number of 100 perſons, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of 60 and vpwards are poore boyes taken out of diuers Pariſhes and ſtreets of this Citie, and now bound Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſes in the ſaid Hoſpitall to be made freemen of this Citty at the end of their ſeuerall Termes.</p>
               <p>I haue but one word more, my laſt part, but one word,
<hi>Whereſoeuer,</hi> of which but a word. <hi>Whereſoeuer,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14038:35"/>the place vnlimited, <hi>infinite,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whereſoeuer. <hi>Salomons</hi> fame neuer went further, the circuit of the <hi>Sunne</hi> is not greater, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vbicunque, vbique.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> was as
<hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, <hi>Abrahams</hi> progenie, <hi>Iobs</hi> familie,
<hi>Nebuchadnezors</hi> furnace, <hi>Eliahs</hi> complaint, but now
<hi>God</hi> is knowne vpon all the <hi>earth,</hi> his ſauing
<hi>health</hi> among all <hi>Nations.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were
<hi>latent,</hi> which the doore <hi>ſhut,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians ſilent,</hi> their liues <hi>couped,</hi> the <hi>Antebunni, hymni,</hi> and priuate <hi>Liturgie</hi> were <hi>ſolitarie;</hi> now God, euen our <hi>owne God,</hi> hath <hi>bleſſed</hi> vs, and all the <hi>ends</hi> of the
<hi>world</hi> ſhall feare him. This <hi>Goſpell,</hi> this
<hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> this <hi>worke,</hi> this <hi>memoriall,</hi> ſhall be whereſoeuer: A <hi>bleſſed worke,</hi> that is ſo <hi>emblazoned. Indi, Scitha, Thraces, Sauromatae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Roffenſis de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tribus Magdal.</note> 
                  <hi>quique Mauritaniam, quique Orthigias Inſulas habitant, quod in domicilio pauperis factum eſt à muliere, magna voce praedicant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome: Et vix pro Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiano habeatur, qui non tenuerit nomen eius,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory.</hi> A holy
<hi>worke</hi> it was that was ſo <hi>honoured,</hi> and it ſo
<hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued,</hi> ſo <hi>repeated,</hi> ſaith <hi>Roffenſis, Singulis annis per totum Chriſtianitatis orbem in celeberrimo Paſchae Feſto per tot Sacerdotum burſas, per tot Pontificum linguas, per tot prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantium tubas, hunc de Maria hymnum pronunciars.</hi> Whereſoeuer this
<hi>Goſpell</hi> is preached: That not onely already <hi>Peter</hi> at
<hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> in all <hi>Aſia, Iames</hi> in
<hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome, Philip</hi> at
<hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> haue long ſince <hi>honoured</hi> this happy <hi>worke</hi> of <hi>Mary:</hi> That
<hi>Timothy</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> at <hi>Crete, Polycarpus</hi> at <hi>Smyrna, Paulinus</hi> at <hi>Nola, Primaſius</hi> at
<hi>Vtica, Eucherius</hi> at <hi>Lyons, Chryſoſtome</hi> at
<hi>Conſtantinople, Cyprian</hi> at <hi>Carthage, Ambroſe</hi> at
<hi>Myllaine, Auſtine</hi> at <hi>Hyppo:</hi> The <hi>glorious company</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>goodly fellowſhip</hi> of the
<hi>Preachers,</hi> the <hi>noble armie</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> the <hi>holy Church</hi> throughout all the world whereſoeuer, doth <hi>knowledge</hi> this memory of the <hi>ointment</hi> of <hi>Mary,</hi> and that the
<hi>memoriall</hi> thereof doth attend the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> Whence iſſueth this laſt <hi>concluſion,</hi> Where the <hi>Goſpell</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14038:35"/>of Chriſts <hi>Paſſion</hi> and
<hi>Reſurrection</hi> is preached,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> there the
<hi>neceſſitie of good workes</hi> ſhould be <hi>vrged:</hi> The
<hi>Reaſon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be the <hi>manifeſt ſignes</hi> of our
<hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>beleefe</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of Chriſt.
<hi>Faith</hi> is ſhewed by <hi>workes,</hi> the <hi>tree</hi> by the
<hi>fruit,</hi> the <hi>ſtreame</hi> by the <hi>fountaine,</hi> the
<hi>light</hi> by the <hi>Sunne.</hi> Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> is he that hath done to vs great things, whereof wee may reioyce, and holy is his <hi>Name.</hi> We muſt performe ſome ſeruice for him to glorifie his <hi>Name.</hi> He hath beene made <hi>poore,</hi> to make vs <hi>rich,</hi> holy is his <hi>Name.</hi> They that be <hi>rich,</hi> ſhould for his ſake ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the
<hi>poore,</hi> to glorifie his <hi>Name.</hi> Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> did euer ſome good worke at the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> which was the greateſt
<hi>Feaſt</hi> of the whole yeere, and the greateſt worke of our
<hi>Redemption</hi> hee performed at this <hi>Feaſt</hi> of the
<hi>Paſſeouer, Holy</hi> is his <hi>Name.</hi> The <hi>act,</hi> the
<hi>feaſt,</hi> the <hi>time,</hi> the <hi>meeting,</hi> the <hi>glad tidings,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of this <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> this
<hi>Goſpell</hi> at the <hi>Paſſeouer,</hi> ſhould bring forth ſome
<hi>fruit</hi> to glorifie his name.</p>
               <p>To <hi>conclude</hi> therefore this laſt <hi>point,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> the <hi>vſe</hi> hereof is to ſtirre vp all of vs to imitate their firſt practiſe, who firſt heard this doctrine of Chriſts <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Acts</hi> 2.23.24.
<hi>Peter</hi> preached to ſome <hi>deuout men</hi> of euery <hi>Nation</hi> vnder heauen, that <hi>Ieſus</hi> whom they had <hi>crucified</hi> and
<hi>ſlaine,</hi> God had raiſed him vp from the <hi>dead:</hi> This was this <hi>Goſpell.</hi> Obſerue from the 41. verſe the fruit of this
<hi>preaching,</hi> they gladly <hi>receiued</hi> this word, 3000. ſoules were added to the <hi>Church:</hi> in the 44. they <hi>beleeued,</hi> and ſold their <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> and <hi>goods,</hi> and
<hi>parted</hi> them to euery man that had need. Here was the <hi>fruit</hi> of their <hi>faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doct.</note> the <hi>true vſe</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> Beloued, let the <hi>ſame minde</hi> be alſo in you. The <hi>Chriſtian Primitiues</hi> were no <hi>Poſſeſſiues:</hi> the <hi>poore</hi> did not <hi>enuie</hi> the <hi>rich, non enim ita diuites,</hi> none were ſo rich, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> the <hi>rich</hi> did not
<hi>deſpiſe</hi> the <hi>poore,</hi> for none were ſo poore. They ſold
<hi>poſſeſſions</hi> to releeue the <hi>neceſſities</hi> and
<hi>wants</hi> of the <hi>Saints:</hi> To
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14038:36"/>doe good therefore, and to diſtribute, forget not; for with ſuch <hi>ſacrifices</hi> God is pleaſed.<note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> And ſuch <hi>ſacrifices</hi> this day haue ye <hi>offered.</hi> Our Sauiour at the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> ſaith
<hi>Rupertus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ert.</note> fed the 5000. the
<hi>number</hi> is great that yee haue <hi>fedde, cloathed, cured;</hi> LONDON is rep eſented here like <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dia the purple ſeller,</hi> or as
<hi>Dorcas</hi> full of <hi>goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes</hi> and <hi>almeſdeeds,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch ſhee hath <hi>done.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>poore men,</hi> and <hi>widdowes,</hi> and
<hi>children</hi> ſhew the <hi>garments</hi> and <hi>coates,</hi> which
<hi>Dorcas</hi> hath made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stant inopes vidu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ij greges &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia morſerant,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exunijs enera a ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld the <hi>beauty</hi> of this <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Syon,</hi> as an <hi>orch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> of <hi>ſweet fruits,</hi> or a <hi>garden</hi> of <hi>ſweet flowers,</hi> as
<hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes</hi> or <hi>Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies,</hi> as a <hi>bed</hi> of <hi>violets,</hi> ſo doe theſe poore <hi>Orphans,</hi> and <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts,</hi> and
<hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> ſoules appeare this <hi>day,</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his <hi>place,</hi> before <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>Angels.</hi> This <hi>Citty</hi> as <hi>Mary</hi> hath powred out her <hi>ointment</hi> on the <hi>body</hi> of our Sauiour, and <hi>annointed</hi> the feete in theſe his <hi>members:</hi> and for this, this whole land is filled with the odour of your ointment.
<hi>Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l honour your memory, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world in the dayes of your <hi>Childrens</hi> children ſhall reioyce in your
<hi>memoriall:</hi> Not <hi>fame</hi> onely, but <hi>God</hi> ſhall make you a <hi>monument,</hi> that ſhall neuer haue an <hi>end.</hi> I hope you haue alſo <hi>annointed</hi> Chriſts head at this <hi>ſolemne</hi> meeting, by celebrating the <hi>great feaſt</hi> of Chriſts <hi>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> to the <hi>glory</hi> of God the <hi>Father,</hi> the ſame minde ſhould be in <hi>vs,</hi> the ſame minde ſhould be <hi>intended</hi> by vs: it was
<hi>his end,</hi> it ſhould be <hi>our end.</hi> To <hi>end</hi> all then, if this be <hi>our end,</hi> why ſhould we doubt but the <hi>Angell</hi> wil deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend at this <hi>time</hi> into the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and ſome <hi>impotent</hi> man that neuer yet did <hi>good</hi> may bee healed? Some dry-<hi>withered</hi>-couetous hand may be cured. You haue duely
<hi>obſerued</hi> Chriſts rule in the <hi>feaſt;</hi> now you keepe the
<hi>feaſt</hi> you haue called the <hi>poore,</hi> and the <hi>ſame,</hi> and the <hi>blinde.</hi> This feaſt is the time that the Iewes kept their feaſt of <hi>firſt fruits.</hi> The firſt fruits of <hi>Zacheus</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14038:36"/>faith are found <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8.
<hi>Behold Lord the halfe of my goods I giue to the poore.</hi> If
<hi>Zacheus</hi> be dead without iſſue, yet at <hi>leaſt,</hi> let euery one doe ſome good, euery one carry home ſome <hi>ſpikenard</hi> to embalme their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for the <hi>buriall,</hi> euery one bring forth ſome fruit of the <hi>reſurrection;</hi> euery one adde ſomewhat to the ioy of the <hi>Angels</hi> in heauen. If all the <hi>Angels</hi> reioyce at the
<hi>converſion</hi> of a ſinner, ô what is the ioy at this
<hi>feast</hi> in heauen, for the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of our Sauiour!
<hi>Euery tree</hi> and <hi>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt,</hi> and <hi>fruit,</hi> and
<hi>flower,</hi> and <hi>herbe</hi> for the vſe of man <hi>creepes</hi> out of the <hi>earth</hi> to celebrate the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt. Doth God cloth the <hi>graſſe</hi> of the earth, the <hi>lillyes</hi> of the <hi>field,</hi> how much more <hi>careth</hi> he for you, ô yee of little <hi>faith?</hi> Let <hi>euery</hi> one at this <hi>feaſt</hi> of
<hi>first fruits,</hi> bring <hi>forth ſome fruit worthy amendment of life.</hi> Euery one hath his <hi>talent,</hi> euery one ſhall beare his owne
<hi>burthen,</hi> euery one ſhall ſtand before the <hi>Tribunall</hi> ſeat of God: euery tree that <hi>bringeth</hi> not forth good <hi>fruit</hi> ſhall be <hi>hewen</hi> downe, and <hi>euery mans</hi> blood ſhall be on his <hi>owne head,</hi> and <hi>tribulation,</hi> and <hi>anguiſh</hi> ſhall be on euery wicked ſoule: but <hi>glory,</hi> &amp; <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>immortalitie</hi> to euery man that <hi>worketh good,</hi> and to the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, and all ſhall liue to the
<hi>glory</hi> of God <hi>the father. Glory be to this God the Father, to Chriſt Ieſus his Sonne our Sauiour, and to the Holy Ghoſt his Spirit our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, as it was in the beginning, ſo now let it be in this place, and in all congregations of the Saints, this day, and all the daies of our liues for euermore. Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
